<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/Schema/master/tei-betamesaheft.rng"
schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/Schema/master/tei-betamesaheft.rng"
type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="mss" xml:lang="en" xml:id="DabraLibanosHamGG1">
<teiHeader xml:base="https://betamasaheft.eu/">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title xml:id="t1" type="académique">Golden Gospel of Beta Mata za-Ham </title>
<editor role="generalEditor" key="AB"/>
<editor key="NV"/>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<p>Photo Credit: Alessandro Bausi © MIE (Missione Italiana in Eritrea 1993-1994),
               Consiglio Nazionale delle Ricerche and University of Bologna.</p>
<p>Photo Credit (the third photos set): Roger Schneider, 1975, invented and scanned by Marie-Laure Derat. © Roger Schneider archive, Institute of Ethiopian Studies, Walda Masqal centre.</p>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<authority>Hiob-Ludolf-Zentrum für Äthiopistik</authority>
<publisher>Die Schriftkultur des christlichen Äthiopiens und Eritreas: Eine multimediale
               Forschungsumgebung / Beta maṣāḥǝft</publisher>
<pubPlace>Hamburg</pubPlace>
<availability>
 <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">
<p> This file is licensed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0.
</p>
 </licence>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<msDesc xml:id="ms">
<msIdentifier>
<repository ref="INS0346DL"/>
<idno facs="Ham/1993/Eri_1993_" n="39">Golden Gospel</idno>
<altIdentifier xml:id="photos1994">
<idno facs="Ham/1994/Eri_1994_" n="19"/>
</altIdentifier>
<altIdentifier xml:id="photos1975">
<idno facs="Ham/1975/" n="24"/>
</altIdentifier>
</msIdentifier>
<physDesc>
<objectDesc form="Codex">
<supportDesc><support>parchment</support>
</supportDesc>
</objectDesc>
<bindingDesc>
<binding contemporary="false">
<decoNote xml:id="b1"> remaining of binding, some new sewing</decoNote>
</binding>
</bindingDesc>
</physDesc>
<additional>
<adminInfo>
<recordHist>
<source>
<listBibl type="catalogue">
<bibl>
<ptr target="bm:Bausi1997ManoscrittiEritreaParteIII"/>
<citedRange unit="page">13-23</citedRange>
</bibl>
</listBibl>
</source>
</recordHist>
</adminInfo>
</additional>
<msPart xml:id="p1">
<msIdentifier></msIdentifier>
<msContents>
<msItem xml:id="p1_i1">
<locus from="1v" to="7r"/>
<title type="complete" ref="LIT4877LetterCanons" xml:lang="geez"/>
<incipit><foreign xml:lang="gez">
<handShift cert="high" corresp="#h1"/>እውሴብስ፡ለቃጲያኖስ፡</foreign>ለዘ፡ኣፈቅር፡እኁየ፡ፍሥሓ፡ወዳኅና፡ለከ፡እምኃቤ፡እግዚአ፡ብሔር፡አሞንስ፡እንከ፡አሌክሰንደርያዊ፡በብዙኅ፡አስተኃምሞ፡ወጺሂቀ፡ገብረ፡</incipit>
<explicit>ወጸሐፍኩ፡ዓዲ፡ውስተ፡ወንጌል፡ትእምርተ፡አኀዘ፡ዘበ፡ሲራክ፡ኀበ፡ገብረ፡ተአምረ፡እግዚእነ፡ኢየሱስ፡ክርስቶስ፡ወኃበሂ፡አዘዘ፡ወኃበሂ፡ገሠጸ፡ወኃበሂ፡መሃረ፡ወኃበሂ፡ነበረ፡ወትእምርተ፡አኀዘ፡ማዕተበ፡መስቀል።</explicit>
</msItem>
</msContents>
<physDesc>
<objectDesc form="Codex">
<supportDesc><support>parchment</support>
</supportDesc>
<layoutDesc>
<layout></layout>
</layoutDesc>
</objectDesc>
<handDesc>
<handNote xml:id="h1" script="Ethiopic" corresp="#p1_i1">
<seg type="script">Monumental script, definitly of type 1a, resembeles the script attested in Abbā Garimā Gospels A and C.
<date cert="medium">fourth/fifth to sixth/seventh century</date>
</seg>
<seg type="ink">brownish, red</seg>
<seg type="rubrication">Red ink was used to layout the letter. Each of three pages has the same mise en texte: three  red lines from the top interchange with the black lines.</seg>
</handNote>
<handNote xml:id="h2" script="Ethiopic" corresp="#a3">
<seg type="script">Monumental script</seg>
<date cert="high">the script can be considered contemporary to <persName ref="PRS6152Lalibala"> <roleName type="title">King</roleName>Lālibālā </persName></date>
<seg type="ink">black</seg>
<note>Some strokes to mark numerals seem to be added later.</note>
</handNote>
<handNote xml:id="h3" script="Ethiopic" corresp="#a4">
<seg type="script">This hand is attested four times at least, in CCR 4, CCR 24, 25 and partially in CCR 1.</seg>
<seg type="ink">brownish</seg>
</handNote>
<handNote xml:id="h4" script="Ethiopic" corresp="#a1">
<seg type="script">This hand is attested three time, in CCR 6 and CCR 14, added in the empty spaces in the Gospel. CCR 14 mentions certain ዐቃቤ ሰዐታት ሰንበት መሓረ and <persName ref="PRS10111WedemR"><roleName type="title">ንጉሥ፡ </roleName>ውድም፡ አርዐድ፡ </persName>, which gives us terminus non ante quem this hand had its additions. </seg>
<seg type="ink">black</seg>
<date cert="medium">1294-1299</date>
</handNote>
<handNote xml:id="h5" script="Ethiopic" corresp="#a2">
<seg type="script"></seg>
<seg type="ink">black</seg>
<date cert="high">This hand seems to be close to the hand attested on f.12rb.</date>
</handNote>
</handDesc>
<decoDesc>
<summary>
According to the foliation introduced by Alessandro Bausi, f.1v contains a big cross of one-page size. It is followed by 11 illustrated pages, ff. 2r-7r. These pages include the Eusebian Apparatus (3+7 arrangement), followed by a «Fontana della vita» or «tempietto» or θόλος, the <term key="ShortCycle">Short Cycle</term>, set under arches made of coloured bands. The manuscript’s decorative features, Bluetenblattstil were not dated precisely, but the XIV century was proposed as a terminus non poste quem. They appear to all be by the same artist.
</summary>
<decoNote type="miniature" xml:id="d1">
<locus target="#1v"/>
The first miniature according to the sequence attested by Carlo Conti Rossini,  Roger Schneider and Alessandro Bausi contains a big cross of one-page size, belonging to the same style as the rest.
</decoNote>
<decoNote type="miniature" xml:id="d2">
<desc> The <title type="complete" ref="LIT1349EpistlEusebius"/> runs between
<locus from="2r" to="3r"/> and is placed under coloured <term key="arch">arches</term>, ornamented variously, that rest on <term key="curtain">curtained</term>
<term key="column">columns</term>.
</desc>
</decoNote>
<decoNote type="miniature" xml:id="d3">
<desc> The <title type="complete" ref="LIT1224Canons"/> run between <locus from="3v" to="6v"/>. The artists
  adopts the same decorative devices used to frame the preceding letter.
The Canons are placed under coloured <term key="arch">arches</term>, ornamented variously, that rest on <term key="curtain">curtained</term>
<term key="column">columns</term>.
</desc>
</decoNote>
<decoNote type="miniature" xml:id="d4">
<locus target="#7r"/>
<desc> A representation of the <ref type="authFile" corresp="AT1034Tempietto"/> follows, as is conventional, the Eusebian
Apparatus. Highly stylized, it features four <term key="column">columns</term>, an <term key="interlace">interlace</term> pattern,
and a low chancel. Above its <term key="cross">cross-topped</term> roof, there are two ostrich <term key="bird">
birds</term>, sitting on the both sides of a tree. The
caption inside the Tempietto, which normally highlights its symbolism, is vanishing but still visible. <q xml:lang="gez"><supplied reason="lost"></supplied>ኑባሬ፡ ሥርዐት፡ ዘኅብሩ፡ አርባዕቱ፡ ወንጌላት።</q>
</desc>
</decoNote>
</decoDesc>
<additions>
<list>
<item xml:id="a1">
<locus target="#1rab"/>
<q xml:lang="gez">
<ab>
<cb n="a"/><handShift cert="high" new="#h4"/>ዘማርያም።እግዚእትየ፡ማርያም፡እስመ፡በዝንቱ፡ደመ፡ወልድ፡ተቀደሱ፡ቅዱሳን፡እስመ፡በዝንቱ፡ኅብስት፡ወበዝንቱ፡ጽዋዐ፡በደኀሪት፡ዕለት፡ኅቱማኒሆሙ፡ይትረከቡ፡ሰአሊ፡ለነ፡ማርያም፡በግርምት፡ዕለት፡ከመ፡ይምሐረነ።
<note>dotted line</note>
ይቤ፡እግዚእ፡አክብሩ፡ሰንበተ፡ተገበሩ፡ጽድቀ፡<handShift cert="low" new="#h5"/>ወፈድፋድስ፡ለማርያም፡አክብርዋ፡እስመ፡ኵሉ፡ዘሰአለ፡ኀቤሃ፡ተዐስዮ፡ፍሥሐ።
<note>dotted line</note>እለ፡ጐዩ፡እምነውር፡እምዝ፡ዓለም፡ነኪር፡እምወርቅ፡ወእምብሩር፡ዘይትበደር፡አክሊለ፡ነሥኡ፡ዘሕብሩ፡ሱሩረ፡ከመ፡እንስሳ፡ገዳም፡ውስተ፡አርእስተ፡አድባር፡ነበሩ፡ከመ፡ኀረ//፡በጻማ፡ተገበሩ፡
<cb n="b"/>እንዘ፡ይጸንሑ፡ብዕለ፡ዘአልቦ፡መምስለ<del/><space/>
</ab>
</q>
</item>
<item xml:id="a2">
<locus target="#1rb"/>
<q xml:lang="gez">
<ab>
<cb n="b"/><handShift cert="high" new="#h5"/>
በስመ፡አብ፡ወወልድ፡ወመንፈስ፡ቅዱስ።ተዝከሩ፡ለበርናባስ፡እም፡፳።ለሶንይ፡ይምሐሮ፡እግዚኣብሔር፡በሰማያት።ወይደምሮ፡ምስለ፡ጻድቃን።።ወለእለ፡ይገብሩ፡ተዝካሮ፡እመሂ፡አንስት፡ወእመሂ፡ተባዕት፡ይምሐሮሙ፡እግዚኣብሔር፡በጸሎቱ፡ወይስረይ፡ኀጢአቶሙ፡ለዓለም፡አሜን።
</ab></q>
</item>
<item xml:id="a3">
<locus target="#7v"/>
<q xml:lang="gez">
<handShift cert="high" new="#h2"/>
<seg ana="#invocation" type="interpretation">በአኰቴተ፡አብ፡ወወልድ፡ወመንፈስ፡ቅዱስ፡</seg>
<seg ana="#suscription" type="interpretation">አ<supplied reason="lost">ጐለት</supplied>ኩ፡አክሰምኩ፡ወአምነይኩ፡አነ፡<persName ref="PRS6152Lalibala"><roleName type="title">ሐፃኒ፡</roleName>ላሊባላ፡ወስመ፡መንግሥትየ፡<addName type="regnal">ገብረ፡መስቀል፡</addName></persName><date calendar="Ethiopian" when="1225" when-custom="409" evidence="internal">
በ፬፻ወ፱፡ዓመተ፡ምሕረት፡አመ፡፫፡ለወርኀ፡<sic>መያዝያ፡</sic></date>ብእሲ፡ዓዛል፡ዘኢይትመዋእ፡ለፀር፡በኀይለ፡መስቀሉ፡ለኢየሱስ፡ክርስቶስ፡ወልደ፡<persName ref="PRS12816Morara">ሞራራ፡</persName>ወልደ፡<persName ref="PRS12817ZanSeyum">ዛን፡ሥዩም፡</persName>ወልደ፡<persName ref="PRS12818Aseda">ኣስዳ፡</persName></seg><seg ana="#provision" type="interpretation">ወሀብኩ፡ለ<placeName ref="LOC2296DabraL" type="church">መጣዕ፡ዘአሀም፡</placeName>ወስ<pb/>
መ፡<persName ref="PRS6859MasqalK">ብእሲትየኒ፡መስቀል፡ክብራ፡</persName>ፈራሂተ፡እግዚብሔር፡<placeName ref="LOC1914Bihat">ቢሐት፡</placeName>በባሕረ፡ኀጸሮ፡እ<add place="above">ን</add>ቀርዖ፡<placeName ref="LOC6447Zareda">ዘሬዳ፡ክርስቲያን፡</placeName>ምስለ፡ምድሮሙ፡በ<add place="above">ን</add>ጽፉ፡ወበቀልቀላ፡<placeName ref="LOC1236Agama">ዓጋማ፡</placeName>ወድዕዱዕ፡ዘኢይበውእ፡ዓቃቤ፡ጸንጸን፡ወኢከንቲባ፡ዘአልቦ፡ግብረ፡ለባዕድ፡ዘእንበለ፡<roleName type="title">አበ፡ምኔት፡ዘ<placeName ref="LOC2296DabraL">መጣዕ፡</placeName></roleName>እመቦ፡ዘተኀየሎ፡ወዘዐገሎ፡ወዘተገሰሶ፡እመሂ፡ዘነግሠ፡ወእመሂ፡ዘአንገሥጋሠ፡ወእመሂ፡ዘተጳጳሰ፡ወእመሂ፡ዘተመኰነነ፡እመሂ፡ሥዩም፡ወእመሂ፡ስዑር፡ወዘተአገሎ፡ለዝንቱ፡ጕልት፡ወለዝንቱ፡ክሱም፡ውጉዘ፡ለይኩን፡በቅድመ፡አብ፡ወወልድ፡ወመንፈስ፡ቅዱስ፡በአፉሁ፡<persName ref="PRS6298Libanos">ለአቡነ፡መጣዕ፡</persName>
በአፈ፡ጳጳሳት፡በኣፈ፡፫፻፲ወ፰፡ርቱዓነ፡ሃይማኖት፡በአፈ፡፲ወ፭፡ነቢያት፡በአፈ፡፲ወ፪፡ሐዋርያት፡አሜን፡ወአሜን።</seg>
<note>Carlo Conti Rossini's edition pp. 189-190 reads በጽፋ for በ<add place="above">ን</add>ጽፉ,<placeName ref="LOC1236Agama">ዓጋማ</placeName> as ዓግማ, አበ፡ምኔት as አባ፡ምኔት, ዘአንገሥጋሠ as ዘአንገሥገሠ, omits በአፈ፡፲ወ፭፡ነቢያት. For this and more see also
<bibl>
<ptr target="bm:Derat2018enigma"></ptr>
<citedRange unit="page">56.</citedRange>
</bibl>
As Roger Scnheider commented in his unpublished notes, 'La version A de Conti Rossini a du se trouver dans la parti du début, parmi les textes varies et n’a pas été photographiée. D’après les variantes graphies de A données par Conti Rossini, la copie plus récente que B. B n’a pas de colonnes. Photo p.2. Ligne pointillée au-dessus du texte.' Marie-Laure Derat's edition, thus, relies on the image taken by Roger Schneider and the apparatus of Conti Rossini for B.
Roger Schneider's transcription of the text reads  ምያዝያ for መያዝያ, በአፉሁ፡ለአቡና፡መጣዕ for በአፉሁ፡ለአቡነ፡መጣዕ.
In the apparatus on p.189 Carlo Conti Rossini provides ጋግማ for ዓጋማ, which is not found in the original.
The copy of this text will be provided further in this discription, here it is important to note that the copy reads እንቀርዖ for what was corrected into እ<add place="above">ን</add>ቀርዖ and በጽንፋ  for what was corrected into በ<add place="above">ን</add>ጽፉ.
</note>
</q>
<q xml:lang="en">
<seg ana="#invocation" type="interpretation">To the glory of the Father and the Son and the Holy Spirit.</seg>
<seg ana="#suscription" type="interpretation">I have assinged gwǝlt, dedicated, secluded, I, <persName ref="PRS6152Lalibala"><roleName type="title">ḥaṣāni</roleName> Lālibālā, my royal name [is] <addName type="regnal">Gabra Masqal</addName></persName><date calendar="Ethiopian" when="1225" when-custom="409" evidence="internal">
    on the third day of the month of <foreign>Mayazya</foreign>in 409th year of mercy, </date>mighty man, who, by the power of the Cross of Jesus Christ is invincible by an enemy, son of <persName ref="PRS12816Morara">Morārā, </persName>son of <persName ref="PRS12817ZanSeyum">Zānsəyum,</persName> son of <persName ref="PRS12818Aseda"> ʾĀsdā, </persName></seg><seg ana="#provision" type="interpretation">I granted <placeName ref="LOC2296DabraL" type="church">Maṭāʿ of ʾAham, </placeName>  the name of<pb/><persName ref="PRS6859MasqalK">my wife [is] Masqal Kəbrā</persName>,fearer of God, Biḥat on the river Ḫaṣaro, ʾƎnqarʿo, christian Zaredā, including their lands  and ʿĀgāmā's steep and Də’du‘,
    where neither ‘āqābē ṣanṣan, nor kantibā should interfere, where no other tax from anyone [sould be] set apart from
<roleName type="title"> ʾabbot of the monastery of <placeName ref="LOC2296DabraL">Maṭāʿ.</placeName></roleName>
  And whoever would violate it or defraud it or withdraw it, whether he would reign or provoke, whether he would be appointed or would hold rulership, whether appointed or displaced,
  who ever will restrain this gwǝlt, and this kǝsum, may he be excommunicated in front of the Father and the Son and the Holy Spirit, by the mouth of our father <persName ref="PRS6298Libanos">Maṭāʿ,</persName>by
  the mouth of ṗāṗāsāt, by the mouth of the 318 orthodox, by the mouth of 15 prophets, by the mouth of 12 apostles, Amen. Amen.</seg>
    </q>
<note>Translation: I am skeptical for my choice, that is why here I provide other choices available:
      I translate here አጐለትኩ፡አክሰምኩ፡ወአምነይኩ as 'I have assinged gwǝlt, dedicated, secluded',
      while the translation found in Roger Schneider's archive offers 'I have given gult, and I have dignified and sanctified', while Derat (p.57) offers 'j'ai donné en gwǝlt, j'ai assingné et j'ai délimité';
    ወሀብኩ፡ለመጣዕ፡ዘአሀም I translate here as 'I granted', Roger Schneider's translator - as 'I have given', Derat - as 'j'ai donné';
ምስለ፡ምድሮሙ፡በንጽፉ፡ወበቀልቀላ፡ዓጋማ I translate here as 'including their lands ʿĀgāmā's steep', Roger Schneider's translator - as 'with their fields, and at its limit and endge Āgmā', while Derat offers 'avec leur terres, à la limite et au ravin d'Agāmā;
ዘኢይበውእ፡ I translate here as 'nor... should interfere', Roger Schneider's translator - as 'nor... shall enter', Derat offers 'n'entre pas';
ዘአልቦ፡ግብረ፡ለባዕድ፡ዘእንበለ፡አበ፡ምኔት፡ዘመጣዕ I translate here as 'where no other tax from anyone [sould be] set apart from',  Roger Schneider's translator - as 'It owes no tribute to an outsider', Derat offers 'sans taxes pour l'étranger';
ለዝንቱ፡ጕልት፡ወለዝንቱ፡ክሱም፡ውጉዘ፡ለይኩን I translate here as '... this gwǝlt, and this kǝsum, may he be excommunicated', Roger Schneider's translator - as 'this gult and dignity... may he be anathematized', while Derat offers 'ce gwǝlt et cette assignation soit excommunié'.
</note>
<note>CCR 7 I parte = [5.0]: (II f. 7v), according to AB. In this case textual varians corresond to "B " in CCR, he comments on p.189  'B scrittura d'età incerta, forse del secolo XVIII.' I did not find any reason not date this document King's Lālibālā postmortem.
      On p. 190 Carlo Conti Rossini notes that 'A questo atto deve certo riferirsi il seguente, che pero nel ms. non trovarsi con esso collegato'. Derat rightly notes on p.55 that in the images done by Roger Schneider, 'les deux parties de l'acte n 7 sont inscrites en continue, au fol. 7v-8r...'. However, as Anais Wion noticed, there is a blank leaf behind the folio in Roger Schneider images, each time when the sequence of folia differs from what later Bausi would observe. This allowed us to conclude that it was Roger Schneider himself who put two folia, containing as he considered two parts of the same document, together. Taking in account this, as well as the formal completeness of the above presented document, I consider it here as full document.
</note>
</item>
<item xml:id="a4">
<locus target="#7v"/>
<q xml:lang="geez">
<handShift cert="high" new="#h3"/>
<seg ana="#invocation" type="interpretation">በአኰቴተ፡አብ፡ወወልድ፡ወመንፈስ፡ቅዱስ፡</seg>
<seg ana="#provision" type="interpretation">ወሀብኩ፡አነ፡ገብረ፡መስቀል፡በአሃም፡፷፡ገራህት፡ለቤተ፡ክርስቲያን፡ወከመ፡ይግ<add>በ</add>ሩ፡ተዝካሮ፡ለመጣዕ፡ከመ፡ይትወሀሰኒ፡በመንግሥተ፡ሰማያት፡እመቦ፡ዘተኀየሎ፡ወዘአገሎ፡ውጉዘ፡ለይ<add>ኩ</add>ን።በአፈ፡አብ፡ወወልድ፡ወመንፈስ፡ቅዱስ። <pb/></seg>
</q>
<q xml:lang="en">
<seg ana="#invocation" type="interpretation"></seg>In the Name of the Father and the Son and the Holy Spirit.
<seg ana="#provision" type="interpretation">I, Gabra Masqal, granted sixty fields of ʾAham to the church, so that they celebrate the commemoration of Maṭāʿ, so that he would beseech a reward for me in the Heavenly Kingdom. If there is someone who would violate it or defraud it, may he be excommunicated by the mouth of the Father and the Son and the Holy Spirit.</seg>
</q>
<note>Translation:
 I translate ወሀብኩ as 'I granted', while Roger Schneider's translator offers 'I have given';
ወከመ፡ይግበሩ፡ተዝካሮ፡ለመጣዕ as 'so that they celebrate the commemoration of Maṭāʿ', while Roger Schneider's translator offers 'so that they may celebrate the commemoration';
ከመ፡ይትወሀሰኒ as 'so that he would beseech a reward for me for me', while Roger Scheider's translator offers 'so that he may be my garantor';
እመቦ፡ዘተኀየሎ፡ወዘአገሎ፡ as 'If there is someone who would violate it or defraud it', while Roger Schneider's translator offers 'whosoever breaks or intringes this'.
</note>
<note>CCR 4 = [5.0]: (II f. 7v), according to AB.  It is page 5 according to Roger Schneider. Carlo Conti Rossini comments on p. 185 : 'Atto indubbiamente apocrifo, che trae dal Gadla Libanos.'
</note>
</item>
</list>
</additions>
</physDesc>
</msPart>
<msPart xml:id="p2">
<msIdentifier>
</msIdentifier>
<msContents>
<msItem xml:id="p2_i1">
<locus target="#8r"/>
<incipit>በ፭፻ወ፭፡ዓመተ፡ምሕረት፡ወሀብኩ፡አነ፡ዐምደ፡ጽዮን፡ንጉሥ፡ለአባ፡መጣዕ፡ዘአሀም፡</incipit>
<explicit>ከመ፡ይትወሐስኒ፡ፍቁርየ፡መጣዕ፡በመንግሥተ፡ሰማያት፡ለዓለመ፡ዓለም፡አሜን። ። </explicit>
<note>[5.0] = CCR 19: (II f. 8r-v), according to AB. Textual variants corresponds to Conti Rossini's "A". Carlo Conti Rossini comments on pp.202-203: 'A scrittura del sec. XVI. La data corrisponde al 1321. Come è noto, <persName ref="@PRS1854Amdase">ʿĀmda Ṣǝyon</persName>, passanti i primi tempi in cui aspramente combattè il clero, fu poi favorevolissime alla chiesa: un ms. del British Museum contiene sue donazioni alla cattedrale di Aksum, la storia delle sue guerre contro l'Adal ne celebra la pietà, e il <title type="complete" ref= 'LIT1438GadlaE'>Gadla ʾEwosṭātewos,</title>che ne ricorda le presecuzioni de'primi anni di regno, ne piange la morte, chiamando "colonna della fede". Nella citata storia delle sue guerre, ed. Perruchon Ṣyon alle pagg. 10, 11, 16, 17, 30-31 sta cetramente a designare Aksum, che ancor oggi è comunemente così chiamata. Degna di osservazione è l'allusione alla poligamia del re, il che concorda pienamente con i dati della storia in quistione. Non potrebbe poi passarsi sollo silenzio la diversità di redazione fra gli atti di questo re e queilli di <persName ref="PRS6152Lalibala">re Lālibālā</persName>'.</note>
</msItem>
<msItem xml:id="p2_i2">
<locus from="8r" to="8v"/>
<title>a prayer about the king</title>
<incipit>ወለንጉሥነ፡ዐምደ፡ጽዮን፡ዘአዕበዮ፡እምነገሥተ፡ምድር፡</incipit>
<explicit>ምስለ፡ዳዊት፡ወቈስጠንጢኖስ፡ወአኖርዮስ፡ለዓለመ፡ዓለም፡አሜን።</explicit>
<note>[5.0] = CCR 19: (II f. 8r-v), according to AB, thus the same comments are applicabale to this part. I, however, decided to split what was considered one document.</note>
</msItem>
<msItem xml:id="p2_i3">
<locus target="#8v"/>
<title>a request for a prayer about the king</title>
<incipit>ወአንትሙሂ፡ቅዱሳን፡እለ፡ሀለውክሙ፡ውስተ፡መካነ፡መጣዕ፡ጸልዩ፡ለንጉሥ፡ዐምደ፡ጽዮን፡</incipit>
<explicit>ወበውስተ፡ማኅበርሂ፡ወኀበ፡ተጋባእክሙሂ፡ለዓለመ፡ዓለም፡አሜን። ።</explicit>
<note>[5.0] = CCR 19: (II f. 8r-v), according to AB, thus the same comments are applicabale to this part. I, however, decided to split what was considered one document.</note>
</msItem>
<msItem xml:id="p2_i4">
<locus from="8v" to="10r"/>
<incipit>በ፭፻፡ወ፯፡ዓመተ፡ምሕረት፡ወሀብኩ፡ኣነ፡ብሌን፡ሰባ፡በዐልተ፡ቢሐት፡ብእሲቱ:ለዐምደ፡ጽዮን፡ንጉሥ፡</incipit>
<explicit>የሀቦ፡እግዚአብሔር፡ትዕግሥተ፡ከመ፡እዮብ፡አሜን።የሀቦ፡እግዚአብሔር፡መዊአ፡ከመ፡ኢያሱ፡አሜን።</explicit>
<note>[5.2-6] = CCR 20: (II ff. 8v-10v), according to AB. I have devided this document into three parts, with of them following next.
Roger Schneider noted in his notes 'The photo is of Conti Rossini's copy A. The text starts on page 6, after CR n 19, from which it is separated by a line of dots and strokes. The text continues on pages 11, 12, 13, and ends on page 14. The writing is similar to that of n 19'. The misplacement, observed by Roger Schneider, seems to be temporary, neither Conti Rossini, nor Alessandro Bausi observed anything similar.
Carlo Conti Rossini commented on pp. 203 and 206 just the following: '"A" scrittura del sec. XVI. [...]. La data corrisponde al 1322. La regina qui nominata è <persName ref="PRS2633BelenSa">Bǝlen Sabā:</persName>nella storia di <persName ref="PRS1854Amdase">re ʿĀmda Ṣǝyon,</persName>riferendosi fatti svoltisi alquanto piu tardi, si parla di <persName ref="PRS10589ZanMan">Žān Mangaśā,</persName>che sembra fosse allora la favorita del re, verosimilmente la "moglie piu giovane" di cui altrove essa parla. Singolare è il nome della regina e da mettersi a paro con quello di Bǝlen Sagad,su di che non potrei che rinviare alle mie <hi rendition="simple:italic">Note etiopiche,</hi> Roma 1894, p.14.
In questo atto, i titolari delle cariche son tutti mutati. La regina stessa Bǝlen Sabā è a capo dell'<placeName ref=" LOC2947Endart">ʾƎntartā,</placeName>precisamente come le figlie di <persName ref="PRS10626ZaraY">re Zarʾa Yāʿqob,</persName>poco piu d'un secolo piu tardi, governavano altre province. Il <hi rendition="simple:italic">mā’ǝkala bāḥr</hi> è non piu il Gabru, che vi trovammo nel 1305, ma un Samāy, che potrebbesi identificare col Semeyšaḥal di cui parla la storia di re ʿĀmda Ṣǝyon a p. 103; nel governo di Dabra Māʿəṣo, Fəqura ʾEgziʾ ha lasciato il posto a Maṭre ʾEgziʾ; lo <hi rendition="simple:italic">ʿaqābe saʿat</hi> di Maṭāʿ è ora Gabra Krəstos, e il <hi rendition="simple:italic">śǝyyuma</hi> Zaredā è  Zarʾa Dāwit, al posto di Yāʿbika ʾEgziʾ'.</note>
</msItem>
<msItem xml:id="p2_i5">
<locus from="10r" to="10v"/>
<incipit>ወለይእቲኒ፡<persName ref="PRS2633BelenSa">ብሌን፡ሰባ፡<roleName type="title">በዐልተ፡ቢሐት፡</roleName></persName>የሀባ፡እግዚኣብሔር፡ፍቅረ፡ምስለ፡<persName ref="PRS1854Amdase"><roleName type="function">ምታ፡</roleName>ዐምደ፡ጽዮን፡</persName></incipit>
<explicit>ወከመ፡ኆጻ፡ባሕር፡አሜን፡ወአሜን።ወይበል፡ኵሉ፡ሕዝብ፡አሜን፡ወአሜን።</explicit>
<note> It is still [5.2-6] = CCR 20: (II ff. 8v-10v), according to AB.</note>
</msItem>
<msItem xml:id="p2_i6">
<locus target="#10v"/>
<incipit>ወኵልክሙ፡እለ፡አንበብክሙ፡ጸልዩ፡</incipit>
<explicit>በሰማይ፡ወበምድር፡ለዓለመ፡ዓለም፡አሜን፡ወአሜን።</explicit>
<note> It is still [5.2-6] = CCR 20: (II ff. 8v-10v), according to AB.</note>
</msItem>
<msItem xml:id="p2_i7">
<locus from="10v" to="11r"/>
<incipit>አነ፡<persName ref="PRS1854Amdase">ዐምደ፡ጽዮን፡</persName>ወሀብኩ፡አንፈ፡በዐት፡ማርያም፡ዘሰዐጋ፡ሕፄን፡</incipit>
<explicit>ወበማርያም፡ወላዲተ፡አምላክ፡ውጉዛነ፡ለይኩኑ፡አሜን።</explicit>
<note>[5.6] = CCR 21: (II ff. 10v-11r), according to AB. Carlo Conti Rossini comments on pp. 206-207 the following: 'Scrittura del secolo XVI. [...]. La data corrisponde al 1323. Alle cariche consuete, i cui titolari non sono mutati, aggiungonsi il seyuma Aṣbi, non nominato, cioe il capo della provincia a NE dell'Enderta, sui contrafforti abissini dominanti il pian del sale e la regione dei Dancali, e l'awfari Degna. Questo Degna è certamente lo stesso che nelle guerre contro l'Adal nel 1332 comandava la cavalleria di destra dell'esercito reale (v. Storia, p.19 e 57); e questo incontro dei due testi è una riprova della loro autenticita. La carica di awfari sembra aver poi raggiunto un grande lustro, come parrebbe dalle donazioni alla cattedrale di Aksum da me odite.'
Roger Schneider notes 'Follows immediately the numbers 20, from which it is separated by a line of dots and strokes. The writing is similar to that of n 20, but the hand is different, a little less trained and slightly smaller. The last line is on page 15'.</note>
</msItem>
<msItem xml:id="p2_i8">
<locus target="#11v"/>
<incipit>አግባእኩ፡አነ፡<persName ref="PRS6073Krestos">ክርስቶስ፡አቡሁ፡</persName>በአፈ፡<persName ref="PRS1854Amdase">ዐምደ፡ጽዮን፡<title>ንጉሥ፡</title></persName>ተርካ፡ዘቀዳሚ፡ምድሮሙ፡ለቅዱሳን፡</incipit>
<explicit>ወእመቦ፡ዘደምሰሳ፡ወዘቀደዳ፡በጽልሑት፡ከማሁ፡ለይኩን፡ውጉዘ፡ለዓለመ፡ዓለም፡አሜን።</explicit>
<note>[5.8] = CCR 18: (II f. 11v), according to Alessandro Bausi.
This document occurs twice, in CCR indicated as "A", 'scrittura del sec. XVI.' on p.201. Carlo Conti Rossini comments on p.202: 'Atto non datato, del tempo di re ʿĀmda Ṣǝyon, che dev'essere stato redatto fra il 1319. Infatti, il capo di Dabra Libānos è, in questo documento, ʿƎqbā ʾƎgziʾ: ora nel 1319 era ancora Asfeḥa, eletto verso la fine del secolo XIII, e nel 1322 era gia Gabra Krestos, che continuava a occupare tale carica ai tempi di re Sayfa Arʿad. ʿƎqbā ʾƎgziʾ va quindi collocato fra i due, e deve essere stato per pochissimo tempo alla direzione del convento.
</note>
</msItem>
</msContents>
<physDesc>
<objectDesc form="Leaf">
<supportDesc><support>parchment</support>
</supportDesc>
<layoutDesc>
<layout></layout>
</layoutDesc>
</objectDesc>
<additions>
<list>
<item xml:id="a5">
<locus target="#11r"/>
<q xml:lang="gez">
  <handShift cert="high" new="#h8"/>
<seg ana="#invocation" type="interpretation">በአኰቴተ፡አብ፡ወወልድ፡ወመንፈስ፡ቅዱስ፡</seg>ወሀብኩ፡አነ፡<persName ref="PRS1854Amdase">አምደ፡ጽዮን፡</persName>ለአባ፡መጣዕ፡ዘንተ፡ጕልተ፡ጽዳእ፡አሲራ፡ለባሲሮ፡ገማእ፡ዜና፡ኩዶ፡አድ፡ሕልሞ፡ኦና፡ሳባይ፡ስናጋ፡ማርያሌ፡ሠርዔ፡ለጎ፡ወንከብ፡ገዳሞሙ፡ለመነኮሳት፡ቤተ፡ሰማእት፡አናንያ፡አዛርያ፡ወሚሳኤል፡ከመ፡ይትወሀሰኒ፡በመንግሥተ፡ሰማያት፡እመቦ፡ዘተአገሎ፡ወዘተኃየሎ፡ውጉዘ፡ለይኩን።
</q>
<q xml:lang="en">
<seg ana="#invocation" type="interpretation">To the glory of the Father and the Son and the Holy Spirit.</seg>
I, <persName ref="PRS1854Amdase">ʿĀmda Ṣǝyon, </persName>granted to ʾabbā Maṭāʿ this gwəlt: Ṣǝdāʾ, ʾAsirā,  Labāsiro, Gamāʾ,  Zenā Kudo, ʾAd Ḥǝlmo, ʾOnā Sābāy, Sənāgā, Māryāle, Sarʿe, Lago, Wankab, the monastery of the monks of the church of martyrs ʾAnānyā, ʾAzāryā and Misāʾel, so that he may beseech a reward for me in the Heavenly Kingdom. If there is anyone who perverts it or violates it, may he be excommunicated.
<note>Translation: Roger Schneider's translator emended  ወሚሳኤል (which I simply translitirate as 'Misāʾel') into 'Michael', noting 'sic' in the square brakets.
ከመ፡ይትወሀሰኒ, which I translate as 'so that he may beseech a reward for me', he interprets as 'so that he may be my garantor' </note>
</q>
<note>[5.6] = CCR 24: (II f. 11r), according to AB. Carlo Conti Rossini comments on p. 211: 'Scrittura del secolo XVII. Atto di dubbia attendibilità, troppo scostandosi dalla forma consueta degli atti di ʿĀmda Ṣǝyon.'
Roger Schneider repeats Conti Rossini, and concludes the following: 'Conti Rossini rightly doubts the authenticity of thic act, because the form of the text differs completely from the one used by ʿĀmda Ṣǝyon. He dates the writing to the XVIIth century. It is very poor and unskilled, difficult to date, but surely late.'
Many of the place names of this act occur in CCR 1 too.
</note>
</item>
<item xml:id="a6">
<locus target="#11rv"/>
<q xml:lang="gez">
<seg ana="#invocation" type="interpretation">በአኰቴተ፡<sic>አከብ፡</sic>ወወልድ፡ወመንፈስ፡ቅዱስ፡</seg>
አግባእኩ፡አነ፡<persName ref="PRS1854Amdase">አምደ፡ጽዮን፡</persName>ዘንተ፡ጕልተ፡ሰማዝ፡ጕናጕና፡ቤት፡ነበይት፡አገርሕሤ፡አዲ፡ግዶም፡ዕፅ፡ማሬ፡አንበሰት፡አጋሜ፡ምስለ፡ምድሮሙ፡ከመ፡ይኵኖ፡መርሐ፡በመንግሥተ፡<pb/>ሰማያት፡ለዓለመ፡ዓለም፡አሜን።
<note>CCR changes አከብ፡ into አብ፡ and ሰማዝ፡ into ከመዝ፡ without noting these emendations (?). In RS transcription is ommited ጕልተ. </note>
</q>
<q xml:lang="en">
<seg ana="#invocation" type="interpretation">To the glory of the Father and the Son and the Holy Spirit.</seg>
I,<persName ref="PRS1854Amdase">ʿĀmda Ṣǝyon,</persName>restored this gwǝlt of Samāz, Gwunāgwunā, Bet Nabayt, ʾAgarḥǝse, ʾAddi Gǝdom, ʿƎṣ Māre, ʾAnbasat, ʾAgāme with theirs lands so that  it may be for him an instructor in the <pb/>Heavenly Kingdom unto the ages of ages, amen.
<note>Translation: As Roger Schneider's translator relied on the edition by Conti Rossini, what I translitirate as 'Samāz', he has as 'Kamaz', noting with a question mark.</note>
<note>[5.6-8] = CCR 25: (II f. 11r-v), according to AB. Carlo Conti Rossini comments on pp.211-212: 'Rozza scrittura, forse del secolo XVII.Ugual osservazione che per l'atto precedente: notisi come l'Agāmē qui apparisca distretto di poca importanza.'
</note>
</q>
</item>
<item xml:id="a7">
<locus target="#11v"/>
<q xml:lang="gez">
<handShift cert="high" new="#h9"/>/>
ምድረ፡ቴድረር፡በሐምሐም፡ቀላይ፡ወባናዕሌ፡ወበአረገን።በክኤቲ፡ፈልግ፡ወኀቦ፡ጕልተ፡ለቅዱስ፡ሊባኖስ፡ንጉሥነ፡ገብረ፡መስቀል፡ከመ፡ይኩኖ፡መርሐ፡በመንግሥተ፡ሰማያት።ዘወሀቦ፡ጕልተ፡ኢይትኴቊ፡እስመ፡ብዙኀ፡ውእቱ፡፡፡፡፡፡፡፡፡፡፡፡፡፡፡፡</q>
<q xml:lang="en">
Land of Tedrar in Ḥamḥam Qalāy and in Nāʿle and in ʾAgaran, in Kǝʾeti Falǝg granted gwǝlt to Holy Libānos King Gabra Masqal, so that he may be a instructor for him in the Heavenly Kingdom. And what was granted as gwǝlt can not be counted, for it is a lot.
</q>
<note>[5.8] = CCR 3: (II f. 11v), according to AB. Carlo Conti Rossini comments on p. 185: 'Scrittura che par del secolo XVIII. [...]. Atto indubitamente apocrifo, che trae origine dal Gadla Libanos'.
</note>
</item>
</list>
</additions>
</physDesc>
</msPart>
<msPart xml:id="p3">
<msIdentifier></msIdentifier>
<msContents>
<msItem xml:id="p3_i1">
<locus target="#12rab"/>
<incipit>ጸሐፍነ፡ኀቢረነ፡ወሠሚረነ፡ተጋቢአነ፡ቅዱሳን፡ዐቃቤ፡ሰዓት፡ዘቤተ፡መጣዕ፡</incipit>
<explicit>በቅድመ፡አብ፡ወወልድ፡ወመንፈስ፡ቅዱስ፡ለዓለመ፡ዓለም፡አሜን፡ወአሜን፡ለይኩን፡ለይኩን፡አሜን።</explicit>
<note>[5.8]: (II f. 12ra-b) [sulla devozione per le vesti di Libānos, non reperibile in CCR], according to AB.
</note>
</msItem>
</msContents>
<physDesc>
<objectDesc form="Leaf">
<supportDesc><support>parchment</support>
</supportDesc>
<layoutDesc>
<layout></layout>
</layoutDesc>
</objectDesc>
<additions>
<list>
<item xml:id="a8">
<locus target="#12rb"/>
<q xml:lang="gez">
ዘአጽሐፍኩ፡አነ፡ሕዝብ፡ሤመ፡ዓቃቤ፡ሰዓት፡ዘቤተ፡መጣዕ፡ትስመር፡ጽዮን፡ገረደ፡መጣዕ፡ወተዳቦ፡ብእሲሃ፡በዘ፡ፈረዩ፡ወጸገዩ፡ገንዞተ፡መጣዕ፡ዘእንበለ፡ዘይትለአኩ፡ለመካን።ለእመቦ፡ዘተሐየሎሙ፡ወተአገሎሙ፡ውጉዘ፡ለይኩን፡በአፈ፡አብ፡ወወልድ፡ወመንፈስ፡ቅዱስ፡
</q>
<note>[5.8.10]: (II f. 12rb e 12vb, bianco f. 12va) [simile al precedente, sulle fasce di Libānos, non reperibile in CCR], according to AB.</note>
</item>
<item xml:id="a9">
<locus target="#12vb"/>
<q xml:lang="gez">
አፈ፡አብ፡ወወልድ፡ወመንፈስ፡ቅዱስ፡ወበአፉሁ፡ለአቡነ፡መጣዕ፡ዓለም፡አሜን።
</q>
<note>[5.8.10]: (II f. 12rb e 12vb, bianco f. 12va) [simile al precedente, sulle fasce di Libānos, non reperibile in CCR], according to AB.</note>
</item>
<item xml:id="a10">
<locus target="#12vb"/>
<q xml:lang="gez">
በ፴ወ፭፡ዓመተ፡ምሕረት፡ወበመዋዕሊሁ፡<persName ref="PRS10626ZaraY">ለንጉሥነ፡ዘርአ፡ያዕቆብ፡ወስመ፡መንግሥቱ፡ቈስጠንጢኖስ፡</persName>ወእምአመ፡ነግሠ፡በ፳ወ፭፡ዓመት፡ዘወሀበ፡ዓምደ፡ለቤተ፡ክርስቲያን፡ዘመጣዕ፡<sic>ተስፈ፡</sic>ኢየሱስ፡ስዩም፡ግሎመከደ፡ወልዱ፡ለይስሞ፡ይበርክ፡ነፍሱ፡ወብእሲቱ፡ወውሉዱ፡ወይጽሐፍ፡ስሞ፡ውስተ፡መጽሐፈ፡ሕይወት፡በጸሎቱ፡ለቅዱስ፡መጣዕ፡ወእንትሙሂ፡ቅዱሳን፡ዝክርዎ፡ወኢትርስዕዎ፡በጸሎትክሙ፡ለዓለመ፡ዓለም፡አሜን
</q>
<q xml:lang="en">
In the 35th year of Mercy, during the days of <persName ref="PRS10626ZaraY">our King Zarʾa Yāʿqob, whose royal name is Qʷasṭanṭinos,</persName>25 years after he became a king, the one who granted a pillar to the church of Maṭāʿ, Tasfā ʾIyasus, səyum of Gəlomakada, son of Yəsmo. May He bless his soul, his wife and his children. May He write his name in the Book of the Life throught the prayers of Saint Maṭāʿ. And you, the holy ones, remember him and do not forget him in your prayers, unto the ages of ages, amen.
  </q>
<note>Conti Rossini emended ተስፈ፡ኢየሱስ as ተስፋ፡ኢየሱስ.Conti Rossini reads ግሎመከደ as .ግሎመከዳ.</note>
<note>[5.10] = CCR 26: (II f. 12vb), according to AB. Conti Rossini comments on p.212: 'Scrittura del secolo XVII (?): colonna. [...]. La data corrisponde al 1459. Il donatore è il capo di Gelo Makada, oggi distretto fra Gunaguna e Addigrat, comprendente anche Dabra Maeso: consta infatti che già nella secondà metà del secolo XIV i capi di quel distretto cominciarono ad aver importanza e ad esercitare una certa influenza sulle regioni crcostanti. Ed è assai probabile che ne'secoli XIII, XIV ecc., non avendo l'Agame. A quanto pare, una unitànpolitica, andasse divso nei feudi di Dabra Maeso (cui poi sarebbe succeduto lo syum di Gelo Makeda), signoreggiante la parte orientale almeno fino agli alti monti ove ora è Endaga Hamus, e di altri capi (p.e. Dabra Damo, di Awgar Sanayt ecc.), che se ne sparvano le terre d'occidente.'</note>
</item>
</list>
</additions>
</physDesc>
</msPart>
<msPart xml:id="p4">
<msIdentifier></msIdentifier>
<msContents>
<msItem xml:id="p4_i1">
<locus target="#13rab"/>
<incipit>ዘወሀቡ፡ቀደምት፡ተርከ፡ለአቡነ፡ሊባኖስ፡ወአነሂ፡ተንሥአ፡ክርስቶስ፡</incipit>
<explicit>ዘኢይትፈታሕ፡በጾም፡ወበጸሎት፡በአፉሁ፡ለአቡነ፡መጣዕ፡አሜን።</explicit>
<note>[5.10] = CCR 29: (II f. 13ra-b), according to AB. Conti Rossini comments on p. 214: 'Grossa scrittura del secolo XVII o XVIII. In due colonne. [...]. Atto di età assolutamente dubbia, anche per lo stato del ms.: l'autore della donazione, confermando al convento il posesso d'un villaggio, doveva essere un capo, di cui cancellature non lasciano indovinare i titoli'.</note>
</msItem>
<msItem xml:id="p4_i2">
<locus target="#13v"/>
<incipit>ወሀብኩ፡አነ፡ይሥምከ፡እግዚእ፡ሥዩመ፡ኀማሳን፡ለአባ፡መጣዕ፡ዘአሀም፡ፈዋሴ፡ዱያን፡</incipit>
<explicit>ቃለ፡መክብብ፡ዘይቤ፡ኵሉ፡ከንቱ፡ከንቱ፡ውእቱ፡ዘኢገብረ፡ሠናየ፡በሕይወቱ።ወበዐጋማሂ፡አርባዕቱዕኩ፡ጕልተ።</explicit>
<note>[5.12] = CCR 28: (II f. 13vb), according to AB. Conti Rossini comments on pp. 213-214: 'Scrittura del secolo XVI: colonna. [...]. Atto non compiuto. Il donatore di schiavi al convento è il capo dello Hamasen, che assime il semplice titolo di sum: nell'atto n.20, che è dell'anno 1328, il capo dello Hamasen è detto awfari, con un vicario (?) chiamato aqansan, ai tempi di re Zara Yaqob aveva invece il titolo di kantiba (J. Perruchon, Les chroniques de Zara Yaqob, p. 48). Riesce quindi impossibile precisare la data dell'atto, che in ogni caso non è posteriore al secolo XVI'.</note>
</msItem>
</msContents>
</msPart>
<msPart xml:id="p5">
<msIdentifier></msIdentifier>
<msContents>
  <msItem xml:id="p5_i1">
    <locus target="#14r"/>
    <incipit></incipit>
    <explicit></explicit>
    <note>[5.12] = CCR 7 II parte: (II f. 14r), according to AB.</note>
    </msItem>
    <msItem xml:id="p5_i2">
      <locus target="#14v"/>
      <incipit></incipit>
      <explicit></explicit>
      <note> [5.14] = CCR 8: (II f. 14v), according to AB.</note>
      </msItem>
</msContents>
<physDesc>
<objectDesc form="Leaf">
<supportDesc><support>parchment</support>
</supportDesc>
<layoutDesc>
<layout></layout>
</layoutDesc>
</objectDesc>
<additions>
<list>
  <item xml:id="a10">
    <locus target="#14r"/>
    <q xml:lang="gez">
    አባ፡መጣዕ፡ዘወሀብክዎ፡አነ፡ገብረ፡መስቀል፡አእሚርየ፡ከመ፡የኃልፍ፡ንብረተ፡ዝንቱ፡ዓለም
    </q>
    <q xml:lang="en">ʾAbbā Maṭāʿ what I, Gabra Masqal, gave, knowing that the possession of the world will pass.
      </q>
      <note>[5.12] = cf. CCR 1: (II f. 14r margine superiore), according to AB.</note>
      </item>
      <item xml:id="a11">
        <locus target="#14v"/>
        <q xml:lang="gez">to transcribe!
          </q>
          <note>[5.14]: (f. 14v) [non reperibile in CCR], according to AB.</note>
          </item>
      </list>
      </additions>
</physDesc>
</msPart>
<msPart xml:id="p6">
<msIdentifier></msIdentifier>
<msContents>
  <msItem xml:id="p6_i1">
    <locus target="#15r"/>
    <incipit>አነ፡ተከሥተ፡ብ<del/>፡ነብር፡እደ፡ሰዐት፡ዘመጣዕ፡<del/>ኩ፡ለመጣዕ፡<del/>ባአ፡፫፡ገራህተ፡</incipit>
    <explicit>በ፩<unclear/>፡ዓመተ፡ምሕረት፡ለዓለመ፡ዓለም፡አሜን፡ወአሜን።</explicit>
    <note>[5.14] = CCR 11: (II f. 15r), according to AB. Carlo Conti Rossini comments on p.195: Scrittura molto arcaica, non posteriore al secolo XIV o XV. Il folio e lacerato in piu punti superiormente, e nell’ultimo tratto l’inchiostro  e in parte svanito, di guisa che l’atto in parte e illegibile'.</note>
    </msItem>
    <msItem xml:id="p6_i2">
      <locus target="#15r"/>
      <incipit>to transcribe</incipit>
      <explicit></explicit>
      <note>[5.14]: (f. 15r) [non reperibile in CCR], accoding to AB.</note>
      </msItem>
        <msItem xml:id="p6_i3">
              <locus target="#15v"/>
              <incipit></incipit>
              <explicit></explicit>
              <note>[5.16] = CCR 10: (II f. 15v), according to AB. Carlo Conti Rossini comments on p. 194 : 'Scrittura del secolo XVI: sul v del folgio su cui e steso l’atto 55. Croce ansata e fregio in margine'.</note>
              </msItem>
              </msContents>
              <physDesc>
              <objectDesc form="Leaf">
              <supportDesc><support>parchment</support>
              </supportDesc>
              <layoutDesc>
              <layout></layout>
              </layoutDesc>
              </objectDesc>
              </physDesc>
              </msPart>
              <msPart xml:id="p7">
              <msIdentifier></msIdentifier>
              <msContents>
                <msItem xml:id="p7_i1">
                  <locus from="16ra" to="17va"/>
                  <incipit>አጽሐፍኩ፡ አነ፡
<subst> <del rend="erasure"/><add place="overstrike">ገብረ፡መስቀል፡</add></subst>
     ንጉሥ።በ፭፻፲ወ፪።ዓመተ፡ ምሕረት፡
</incipit>
                  <explicit>የሀቦ፡ እግዚአብሔር፡ ጥበበ፡ ከመ፡ ሰሎሞን፡ አሜን።የሀቦ፡ እግዚኣብ
</explicit>
                  <note>[5.16-20] = CCR 22: (II ff. 16ra-17vb), according to AB.</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="p7_i2">
                    <locus target="#17v"/>
                    <title type="incomplete">a prayer about the king</title>
            <incipit>
                ወለንጉሥነ፡<subst><del rend="erasure"/><add place="overstrike">ገብረ፡መስቀል፡</add></subst>የሀቦ፡እግዚአብሔር፡<sic>መንግሥተ፡ሰማያት፡</sic>ህየንተ፡ሕዳጥ፡ብዙኅ፡አሜን።</incipit>
              <explicit>
                ወያግርር፡ጸሮ፡ወጻላእቶ፡አሜን።ወይስረይ፡ኃጢአቶ፡ወይደምስስ፡መጽሐፈ፡ዕዳሁ፡አሜን።
                የሀቦ፡እግዚአብሔር፡ጥበበ፡ከመ፡ሰሎሞን፡አሜን።
                የሀቦ፡እግዚኣብ</explicit>
              </msItem>
                </msContents>
                <physDesc>
                <objectDesc form="Leaf">
                <supportDesc><support>parchment</support>
                </supportDesc>
                <layoutDesc>
                <layout>two columns</layout>
                </layoutDesc>
                </objectDesc>
                </physDesc>
                </msPart>
                <msPart xml:id="p8">
                <msIdentifier></msIdentifier>
                <msContents>
                  <msItem xml:id="p8_i1">
                    <note>[5.20] = CCR 17: (II f. 18r), according to AB.</note>
                  </msItem>
                    <msItem xml:id="p8_i2">
                      <note>[5.22] = CCR 27: (II f. 18v), according to AB.</note>
                      </msItem>
                  </msContents>
                  <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc form="Leaf">
                  <supportDesc><support>parchment</support>
                  </supportDesc>
                  <layoutDesc>
                  <layout>two columns</layout>
                  </layoutDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  <additions>
                  <list>
                    <item xml:id="a12">
                      <locus target="#18v"/>
                      <q xml:lang="gez">
                        </q>
                        </item>
                  </list></additions>
                  </physDesc>
                  </msPart>
                  <msPart xml:id="p9">
                  <msIdentifier></msIdentifier>
                  <msContents>
                    <msItem xml:id="p9_i1">
                      <note>[5.22] = CCR 12: (II f. 19r), according to AB.</note>
                      </msItem>
                        <msItem xml:id="p9_i2">
                          <note>[5.22] = CCR 13: (II f. 19r), according to AB.</note>
                          </msItem>
                          <msItem xml:id="p9_i3">
                            <note>[5.23] = CCR 15: (II ff. 19va-20va), according to AB.</note>
                            </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                    <objectDesc form="Leaf">
                    <supportDesc><support>parchment</support>
                    </supportDesc>
                    <layoutDesc>
                    <layout>two columns</layout>
                    </layoutDesc>
                    </objectDesc>
                    <additions>
                    <list>
                      <item xml:id="a13">
                        <locus target="#19r"/>
                        <q xml:lang="gez">
                          </q>
                          <note>[5.22]: (f. 19r) [quasi illeggibile e non reperibile in CCR], according to AB.</note>
                          </item>
                            <item xml:id="a14">
                              <note>[5.24] = CCR 32: (II f. 20va-b), according to AB.</note>
                              </item>
                                <item xml:id="a15">
                                  <note>[5.24] = CCR 16: (II f. 20vb), according to AB.</note>
                                  </item>
                                      <item xml:id="a16">
                                        <note>[5.24] = CCR 5: (II f. 20vb), according to AB.</note>
                                        </item>
                    </list></additions>
                    </physDesc>
                    </msPart>
                    <msPart xml:id="p10">
                    <msIdentifier></msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem xml:id="p10_i1">
                          <note>[5.24] = CCR 23: (II ff. 21ra-va), according to AB.</note>
                          </msItem>
                            <msItem xml:id="p10_i2">
                              <note>[5.25-6.0] = CCR 33: (II ff. 21va-22rb), according to AB.</note>
                              </msItem>
                      </msContents>
                      <physDesc>
                      <objectDesc form="Leaf">
                      <supportDesc><support>parchment</support>
                      </supportDesc>
                      <layoutDesc>
                      <layout>two columns</layout>
                      </layoutDesc>
                      </objectDesc>
                      <additions>
                      <list>
                          <item xml:id="a17">
                            <q xml:lang="gez">
                              </q>
                            <note>[6.1]: (II f. 22va) [lista dei beni della Chiesa di Maṭā‘, non reperibile in CCR], according to AB.</note>
                            </item>
                            </list>
                            </additions>
                            </physDesc>
                            </msPart>
    <msPart xml:id="p11">
      <msIdentifier></msIdentifier>
      <msContents>
          <msItem xml:id="p11_i1">
            <note>[6.1] = CCR 6 I parte: (II f. 23ra-b), according to AB.</note>
            </msItem>
        </msContents>
        <physDesc>  <objectDesc form="Leaf">
          <supportDesc><support>parchment</support>
          </supportDesc>
          <layoutDesc>
          <layout>two columns</layout>
          </layoutDesc>
          </objectDesc>
      </physDesc>
      </msPart>
      <msPart xml:id="p12">
        <msIdentifier></msIdentifier>
        <msContents>
          <msItem xml:id="p12_i1">
          <note></note>
          </msItem>
          </msContents>
          <physDesc>  <objectDesc form="Codex">
            <supportDesc><support>parchment</support>
            </supportDesc>
            <layoutDesc>
            <layout>two columns</layout>
            </layoutDesc>
            </objectDesc>
            <additions>
              <list>
                <item xml:id="a18">
                  <q xml:lang="gez">
                    </q>
                    <note>The text corresponds to CCR 14. This document was photographed only by Roger Schneider.</note>
                    </item>
                    <item xml:id="a19">
                      <q xml:lang="gez">
                        </q>
                        <note>The text corresponds to CCR 31. This document was photographed only by Roger Schneider.</note>
                        </item>
                        <item xml:id="a20">
                          <q xml:lang="gez">
                            </q>
                            <note>The text corresponds to CCR 9. This document was photographed only by Roger Schneider.</note>
                            </item>
              </list>
            </additions>
        </physDesc>
        </msPart>
      <msPart xml:id="p13">
        <msIdentifier></msIdentifier>
        <msContents>
          <msItem xml:id="p13_i1">
          <note></note>
          </msItem>
          </msContents>
          <physDesc>  <objectDesc form="Codex">
            <supportDesc><support>parchment</support>
            </supportDesc>
            <layoutDesc>
            <layout>two columns</layout>
            </layoutDesc>
            </objectDesc>
            <additions>
              <list>
                <item xml:id="a21">
                  <q xml:lang="gez">
                    </q>
                    <note>[4.34]: (I f. 11ra-b) [non reperibile in CCR], according to AB.</note>
                    </item>
                    <item xml:id="a22">
                      <q xml:lang="gez">
                        <note>[4.36] = CCR 1: (I f. 11va-b), according to AB.</note>
</q>
</item>
              </list>
            </additions>
        </physDesc>
        </msPart>
      <msPart xml:id="p14">
        <msIdentifier></msIdentifier>
        <msContents>
          <msItem xml:id="p14_i1">
          <note>[4.18-22] = CCR 22: (I ff. 3ra-4vb), according to AB.</note>
          </msItem>
          <msItem xml:id="p14_i2">
          <note>[4.22-26] = CCR 20: (I ff. 4vb-6vb), according to AB.</note>
          </msItem>
          <msItem xml:id="p14_i3">
          <note>[4.26-28] = CCR 19: (I ff. 6vb-7vb), according to AB.</note>
          </msItem>
          <msItem xml:id="p14_i4">
          <note>[4.28-30] = CCR 7: (I ff. 7vb-9ra), according to AB.</note>
          </msItem>
          <msItem xml:id="p14_i5">
          <note>[4.30] = CCR 18: (I f. 9ra-b), according to AB.</note>
          </msItem>
          <msItem xml:id="p14_i6">
          <note>[4.30-32] = CCR 33: (I ff. 9rb-10rb), according to AB.</note>
          </msItem>
          <msItem xml:id="p14_i7">
          <note>[4.34] = CCR 34: (I f. 10va-b), according to AB.</note>
          </msItem>
          </msContents>
          <physDesc>  <objectDesc form="Codex">
            <supportDesc><support>parchment</support>
            </supportDesc>
            <layoutDesc>
            <layout>two columns</layout>
            </layoutDesc>
            </objectDesc>
        </physDesc>
        </msPart>
                </msDesc>

</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/Documentation/master/prefixDef.xml">
<xi:fallback>
<p>Definitions of prefixes used.</p>
</xi:fallback>
</xi:include>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="en">English</language>
<language ident="it">Italian</language>
<language ident="gez">Gǝʿǝz</language>
</langUsage>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
 <change who="ES" when="2018-06-01">Created stub record</change>
 <change who="PL" when="2019-06-28">some fixes for validation</change>
<change who="NV" when="2019-11-20">updates</change>
<change who="NV" when="2019-11-26">encoded Decodesc</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text xml:base="https://betamasaheft.eu/">
<body>
  <div type="edition"  xml:lang="gez" corresp="#p2_i1">
<div type="textpart" subtype="folio" n="8r">
<ab>
  <handShift cert="high" new="#h6"/>
  <seg ana="#invocation" type="interpretation">በአኰቴተ፡አብ፡ወወልድ፡ወመንፈስ፡ቅዱስ፡
  </seg>
  <seg ana="#subscription" type="interpretation">በ፭፻ወ፭፡ዓመተ፡ምሕረት፡ወሀብኩ፡አነ፡
    <persName ref="PRS1854Amdase">ዐምደ፡ጽዮን፡<roleName type="title">ንጉሥ፡</roleName></persName>ለአባ፡መጣዕ፡ዘአሀም፡ከመ፡ይትወኀሰኒ፡በመንግሥተ፡ሰማያት።
  </seg><seg ana="#provision" type="interpretation">ወርቅ፡፻፹ወ፪፡፪፡መስቀል፡ዘወርቅ፡ወ፩፡ጻሕል፡ዘወርቅ፡ወ፩፡ጽዋዕ፡ዘወርቅ።ወ፩፡ጻሕል፡ዘብሩር፡ወ፩፡ጽዋዕ፡ዘብሩር።ወአልባስ፡ክቡር፡፻፫፡ለቤተ፡ክርስትያን፡ዘመጣዕ፡ወለቅዱሳንሂ፡፵፡ብዙት፡ወለካልኣንሂ፡አብያተ፡ክርስትያን፡እለ፡ውስተ፡ሀገሩ፡፴፡ልብስ፡ክቡራት፡ወአልህምትሂ፡፲፻፡ወእምድኅረ፡ኵሎን፡ወሀብኩ፡ልብሰ፡ወርቅ፡ዘላዕሌየ፡ወዕጣቅየ፡ወ፪፡<sic>ስራዌልየ፡</sic>አውጺእየ፡እምውስተ፡ሐቌየ፡ወ፪፡አሣእንየ፡እምእገርየ።ወዘንተ፡ኵሎ፡ዘወሀብኩ፡አእሚርየ፡ከመ፡የሐልፍ፡ንብረተ፡ዝንቱ፡ዓለም፡ከመ፡ይትወሐስኒ፡ፍቁርየ፡መጣዕ፡በመንግሥተ፡ሰማያት፡ለዓለመ፡ዓለም፡አሜን። ። </seg>
<note>The edition by Carlo Conti Rossini on p.202 contains በ፭፪ወ፭ instead of በ፭፻ወ፭, which seems to be a simple type-error, for non of the witnesses contain this date and it is not marked in the apparatus. It is proved by the date, 1321, which Carlo Conti Rossini must have counted from በ፭፻ወ፭.
Further, it reads ውስተ፡ሀገሩ፡ዘመጣዕ, while it is ውስተ፡ሀገሩ in the manuscript, ወአልህምትሂ፡፲፪ instead of ወአልህምትሂ፡፲፻,ሰራዌልየ instead of <sic>ስራዌልየ</sic> and እሳየ instead of አሣእንየ.
</note>
</ab>
</div>
</div>
<div type="edition"  xml:lang="en" corresp="#p2_i1">
<div type="textpart" subtype="folio" n="8r">
<ab><seg ana="#invocation" type="interpretation">
To the glory of the Father and the Son and the Holy Spirit.
</seg>
<seg ana="#subscription" type="interpretation">in 505 year of mercy, I, king ʿAmda Ṣǝyon, granted ’abbā Maṭā‘ of ’Aham so that he would beseech a reward for me in the Heavenly Kingdom,
</seg>
<seg ana="#provision" type="interpretation">182 [pieces] of gold, two crosses of gold and one dish of gold and one chalice of gold, one dish of silver and one chalice of silver, 103 rich vestments to the church of Maṭā‘ and to the holy ones 40 fine cloths, and 30 rich vestments and 1000 cows to the other churches in his land. And after all, I gave my own golden robe and my weapon and  my two pans taken from my hip, and my pair of shoes from my feet. And all this I gave, knowing that the wealth of this world  will pass, so that beloved Maṭā‘ would beseech a reward for me the Heavenly Kingdom, forever and ever, Amen.
</seg>
<note>As Roger Schneider's translator relied on the edited text, his translation reads as "In the year of Mercy 525 year'; not 'in his land' but 'inside the land of Maṭā‘'; '12 cows' instead of 1000; ሰራዌልየ remains untranslated. Then, as was mentioned, I made a choice for as 'would beseech a reward for me for me', while Roger Scheider's translator offers 'may be my garantor'.
</note>
</ab>
</div>
</div>
<div type="edition"  xml:lang="gez" corresp="#p2_i2">
<div type="textpart" subtype="folio" n="8rv">
<ab>
ወለ<persName ref="PRS1854Amdase"><roleName type="title">ንጉሥነ፡</roleName>ዐምደ፡ጽዮን፡</persName>ዘአዕበዮ፡እምነገሥተ፡ምድር፡ያኑኅ፡መዋዕሊሁ፡በዲበ፡ምድር፡ወይረስዮ፡እግዚኣብሔ፡ሥሩዐ፡ከመ፡ወርኅ፡ወብሩሀ፡ከመ፡ፀሓይ፡ወይዕቀብ፡አንስትያሁ፡ወደቂቁ፡ወደቂቀ፡ደቂቁ፡ወዓዲ፡ያድኅኖሙ፡ለሰራዊቱ፡እምስረተ<damage/>፡ኀጽ፡ወውግረተ፡እብን።ወያግርር፡<pb/>ጸሮ፡ወጻላእቶ፡በዕለተ፡ሞቱሂ፡ይኈልቆ፡ምስለ፡ቅዱሳን፡ወሰማዕት፡ምስለ፡እለ፡አስመርዎ፡ለእግዚኣብሔር፡ምስለ፡ዳዊት፡ወቈስጠንጢኖስ፡ወአኖርዮስ፡ለዓለመ፡ዓለም፡አሜን።
</ab>
</div>
  </div>
  <div type="edition"  xml:lang="en" corresp="#p2_i2">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="folio" n="8rv">
  <ab>
    And for our King ʿAmda Ṣǝyon, who was made the greatest among the kings on the earth, may God extend his days on the earth and may God make him set firmly as the Moon and splendid as the Sun and may He protect his wives and his children and children of his children and may He save his army from the flying dart and from throwinging of a stone. And may He subdue his enemy and his adversaries. And on the day of his death, may He count him among the saints and martyrs and among those who pleased God, with Dawit and Qwosṭanṭinos and ʾAnoryos, for ever and ever, Amen.
<note>Translation:
What I translate as 'who was made the greatest among the kings on the earch', Roger Schneider's translator offers 'whom he has elevated above the kings of the earch'; for my 'splendid as the Sun' he offers 'bright as the Sun'; for my 'may He protect his wives...' he offers 'may he keep his wives'; for my 'may He save his army from the flying dart' he offers 'may he protect his armies from the piercieng of arrows'; for my 'from throwinging of a stone' he offers 'from being crushed by stones'; for my 'those who pleased God' he offers 'among those who exalted God'.</note>
    </ab>
    </div>
    </div>
    <div type="edition"  xml:lang="gez" corresp="#p2_i3">
    <div type="textpart" subtype="folio" n="8v">
    <ab>ወአንትሙሂ፡ቅዱሳን፡እለ፡ሀለውክሙ፡ውስተ፡መካነ፡መጣዕ፡ጸልዩ፡ለ<persName ref="PRS1854Amdase"><roleName type="title">
      ንጉሥ፡</roleName>ዐምደ፡ጽዮን፡</persName>ሰርከ፡ወነግሀ፡ሌሊት፡ወምዐልተ፡ቀትረ፡ወሰዐተ፡በውስተ፡ቊርባንሂ፡ወበውስተ፡ማኅበርሂ፡ወኀበ፡ተጋባእክሙሂ፡ለዓለመ፡ዓለም፡አሜን። ።
      </ab>
      </div>
    </div>
    <div type="edition"  xml:lang="en" corresp="#p2_i3">
    <div type="textpart" subtype="folio" n="8v">
      <ab>And you, the holy ones, those who dwells in the place of Maṭāʿ, pray for the King ʿAmda Ṣǝyon, at the evenings and at the daybreak, at time of noons, and at the hour of Qwǝrbān and during the māḫbar and by assembling, forever and ever, Amen.
      </ab>
      </div>
      </div>
      <div type="edition"  xml:lang="gez" corresp="#p2_i4">
      <div type="textpart" subtype="folio" n="8v10r">
        <ab>
          <seg ana="#invocation" type="interpretation">በአኰቴተ፡አብ፡ወወልድ፡ወመንፈስ፡ቅዱስ።</seg>
          <seg ana="#subscription" type="interpretation">በ፭፻፡ወ፯፡ዓመተ፡ምሕረት፡ወሀብኩ፡አነ፡
            <persName ref="PRS2633BelenSa">ብሌን፡ሰባ፡በዐልተ፡ቢሐት፡ብእሲቱ:</persName>ለ<persName ref="PRS1854Amdase">ዐምደ፡ጽዮን፡<roleName type="title">ንጉሥ፡</roleName></persName>በእንተ፡ፍቅሩ፡ለመጣዕ፡ከመ፡ይትወኀሰኒ፡በመንግሥተ፡ሰማያት፡አመ፡እቀውም፡ዕሬቅየ፡ቅድመ፡ሰማያዊ፡ንጉሥ፡
          </seg>
          <seg ana="#provision" type="interpretation">ገለባ፡ወእንቀርዖ፡ወሀብኩ፡ዘንተ፡ጕልተ፡ለብፁዕ፡መጣዕ፡ፍቁርየ፡<sic>ዘኢይበኦ፡</sic>ፈረስ፡ወኢአንበሳ፡ወኢስዩመ፡ደብረ፡ማዕጾ፡ወኢስዩመ፡ዘሬዳ፡ኢዘተሰይመ፡ወኢዘተስዕረ፡ኢዘነገሠ፡ወኢዘአንገስገሰ፡ዘኢይ
          <pb n="9r"/>
በኦ፡<sic>ቃል፡</sic>ነጋሲ፡ወኢደቀ፡ጽርኅ፡ወለእመቦ፡ዘተአገለ፡ወዘተኀየለ፡ዘንተ፡ጕልተ፡ዘወሀብኩ፡ለአባ፡መጣዕ፡ዘአሀም፡እንዘ፡<persName ref="PRS1854Amdase"><roleName type="title">ንጉሥ፡</roleName>ዐምደ፡ጽዮን፡</persName>ወእንዘ፡
<persName ref="PRS2633BelenSa"><title>ስይምተ፡እንትርታ፡</title>ብሌን፡ሰባ፡<title>በዐልተ፡ቢኀት፡</title></persName>
ወእንዘ፡ማእከለ፡ባሕር፡ሰማይ፡
ወእንዘ፡ስዩመ፡ደብረ፡ማዕጾ፡መጥሬ፡እግዚእ፡
ወእንዘ፡ስዩመ፡ዘሬዳ፡ዘርአ፡ዳዊት፡
ወእንዘ፡ዐቃቤ፡ሰዐተ፡መጣዕ፡ገብረ፡ክርስቶስ፡
ወዘንተ፡ዘወሀብኩ፡አእሚርየ፡ከመ፡የሐልፍ፡ኵሉ፡ዓለም፡ወሰማዕኩ፡ዘይቤ፡ቃለ፡መክብብ፡ከንቱ፡ኵሉ፡ከንቱ፡ዘእንበለ፡ዘአቅደመ፡ስንቁ፡በሒወቱ፡ወአነሂ፡ወሀብኩ፡ለመጣዕ፡ወለቅዱሳን፡፻ወ፶፡አልህምት፡ወ፳፡ልብሰ፡ሰንዶናት፡ወመባእሂ፡ጽዒንየ፡ዘአውረድኩ፡በአምኀራ። ። ፡
ወእመቦ፡ዘተኀየለ፡ዘንተ፡ጕልተ፡ዘወሀብኩ፡አነ፡ለመባእ፡ወለተዝካሩ፡ለመጣዕ፡ፍቁርየ፡ውጉዘ፡ለይኵን፡በአፈ፡፲ወ፭፡ነቢያት፡ወበአፈ፡፲ወ፪፡ሐዋርያት፡በአፈ፡፫፻፲ወ፰፡ርቱዐነ፡ሃይማኖት፡ወበአፈ፡ጴጥሮስ፡ሊቀ፡ጳጳሳት፡ወበጸሎቱ፡ለብፁዕ፡መጣዕ፡ወበአፈ፡አብ፡ወወልድ፡ወመንፈስ፡ቅዱስ፡ውጉዘ፡ለይኵን፡በዝ፡ዓለም፡
<pb n="9v"/>ወበዘ፡ይመጽእ፡ዓለም፡ዘኢይትፈታሕ፡በጾም፡ወበጸሎት፡በስኢል፡ወበሰጊድ፡ለዓለመ፡ዓለም፡አሜን።
ወ<space/>ዘአግባእኩ፡ዘንተ፡ጕልተ፡<space/>ወዘንተ፡ኵሎ፡ዘገበርኩ፡ዘአዘዘኒ፡<persName ref="PRS1854Amdase"><roleName type="title">እግዚእየ፡ንጉሥ፡
</roleName>ዐምደ፡ጽዮን፡</persName>ወይቤለኒ፡ሖሪ፡ብጽሒ፡ኀበ፡መጣዕ፡ዘአሀም፡ወግበሪ፡ፈቃዶ፡ለብፁዕ፡መጣዕ፡<sic>ፍቁ<supplied reason="omitted">ር</supplied>የ፡</sic>ወበሊ፡ኢትንሥኦ፡እግዚኦ፡በመዋዕለ፡ውርዙቱ፡<persName ref="PRS1854Amdase"><roleName type="title">ለእግዚእየ፡</roleName>ዐምደ፡ጽዮን፡</persName>ወበጻሕኩ፡አነኒ፡ወበከይኩ፡ወላሐውኩ፡ወአንገርገርኩ፡ኀበ፡መቃብሩ፡ለመጣዕ፡በከመ፡አዘዘኒ፡<persName ref="PRS1854Amdase"><roleName type="title"><sic>እግዚዚየ፡
</sic></roleName>ዐምደ፡ጽዮን፡</persName>ግበር፡ሎቱ፡እግዚኦ፡በከመ፡ፈቃደ፡ልቡ፡ወይቤለኒ፡ሀቢ፡እንቀርዖ፡ወገለባ፡ከመ፡የሀበኒ፡እግዚኣብሔር፡በመንግሥተ፡ሰማያት፡ህየንተ፡ኅዳጥ፡ብዙኅ፡አሜን፡የሀቦ፡እግዚኣብሔር፡ህየንተ፡ንስቲት፡ዐቢየ፡አሜን።የሀቦ፡እግዚኣብሔር፡ህየንተ፡ዘበምድር፡ዘበ፡ሰማያት፡አሜን።ህየንተ፡ዘይበሊ፡ዘኢይበሊ፡አሜን።ወህየንተ፡ዘይማስን፡ዘኢይማስን፡አሜን።ወያኑኅ፡መዋዕሊሁ፡በዲበ፡ምድር፡አሜን።ወያግርር፡ጸሮ፡<pb n="10r"/>ወጻላእቶ፡አሜን።
ወይስረይ፡ኀጢአቶ፡ወይደምስስ፡መጽሐፈ፡ዕዳሁ፡አሜን።የሀቦ፡እግዚአብሔር፡ጥበበ፡ከመ፡ሰሎሞን፡አሜን።የሀቦ፡እግዚአብሔር፡ሞገሰ፡በከመ፡ዳዊት፡አሜን።የሀቦ፡እግዚአብሔር፡ትዕግሥተ፡ከመ፡እዮብ፡አሜን።የሀቦ፡እግዚአብሔር፡መዊአ፡ከመ፡ኢያሱ፡አሜን።
</seg>
<note>Roger Schneider, as I can judge from his transcription, read ከመ፡ይወኀሰኒ what I read as ከመ፡ይወኀሰኒ, this must be a simple error. Roger Schneider read  ዕራቅየ what I read as ዕሬቅየ and what Carlo Conti Rossini on p. 20 read as ዕረቅየ. Roger Schneider reads ኢዘተሰይም what I read as ኢዘተሰይመ, what also seems to be a simple error by transcribing. To ኢዘነገሠ Roger Schneider gives a comment that 'Sic ms. Read probably ነግሠ፡ Conti Rossini, p. 204, line 1, gives ተነግሠ, but this form is not otherwise attested'. In the photo by Alessandro Bausi the reading is as I present here.  What I read as ወ፳፡ልብሰ, Roger Schneider read as ወአ፡ልባሰ, while Carlo Conti Rossini read as ወአልባስ. This reading is not clear, but there are definetly two dotts after two first characters. በ፭፻፡ወ፯ Carlo Conti Rossini reads on p. 203 as በ፭፻፡ወ፮, ብሌን፡ሰባ as ብሌን፡ሳባ, noting ብሌን፡ሰባ as a variant reading in "A". ዘኢይበኦ ܸConti Rossini emended on the basis of "B" reading as ዘኢይበውኦ two times. ቃል፡ነጋሲ Conti Rossini reads as ቃለ፡ነጋሲ, which is also in "B", but it is not marked in the apparatus. ስይምተ፡እንትርታ Conti Rossini reads as ሠየምተ፡እንትርታ, which can not be interpreted otherwise as an error. ወበዘ፡ይመጽእ Conti Rossini read as ወበዝ፡ይመጽእ. እግዚእየ፡ንጉሥ Conti Rossini erroneously read እግዚእነ፡ንጉሥ. Conti Rossini emended ሖሪ as ሑሪ.
At the end Roger Schneider notes in brackets that 'a line of dots and strokes as a separation.'</note>
</ab>
</div>
</div>
<div type="edition"  xml:lang="en" corresp="#p2_i4">
<div type="textpart" subtype="folio" n="8v10r">
  <ab>
    <seg ana="#invocation" type="interpretation">To the glory of the Father and the Son and the Holy Spirit.</seg>
<seg ana="#subscription" type="interpretation">
In the 507th year of Mercy, I,<persName ref="PRS2633BelenSa">Bǝlen Sabā,<title>the lady of Biḥat,</title></persName>wife of<persName ref="PRS1854Amdase">
ʿĀmda Ṣǝyon,<roleName type="title">the king,</roleName></persName>because of the love to Maṭāʿ, so that he would beseech a reward for me in the Heavenly Kingdom, while I shall stay naked infront of the Heavenly King, <placeName ref="LOC3198Galaba">Galabā</placeName>and ʾƎnqarʿo, I gave this gwəlt to blessed Maṭāʿ, my beloved, which should not penestrate neither a horse nor a lion, neither a sǝyum of Dabra Māʿəṣo nor a sǝyum of Zaredā, neither an appointed one, nor the deposed one, neither the one who reigns nor who is agitated, neither
<pb n="9r"/>
the spokesman of nǝguś, nor children of the palace.
And if there is anyone who frauds or violates this gwəlt, which I granted to ʾabbā Maṭāʿ of ʾAham, while the <persName ref="PRS1854Amdase"><roleName type="title">king</roleName>ʿĀmda Ṣǝyon</persName>and while
the sǝyum of <placeName ref="LOC2947Endart">ʾƎntartā </placeName> <persName ref="PRS2633BelenSa"> Bǝlen Sabā <title>the lady of Biḥat</title></persName>
and while <persName ref="PRS8449Samay"><title>māʾǝkala baḥǝr</title> Samāy,</persName>
and while sǝyum of Dabra Māʿəṣo Maṭre ʾEgziʾ,
and while sǝyum of Zaredā Zarʾa Dāwit,
and while ʿaqābe saʿata Maṭāʿ Gabra Krəstos.
I gave this, knowing that the whole world will pass, and I have heard the word of Ecclesiastes saying, 'Vanity, all is vanity, unless one prepares his provisions beforehead alive'. And I gave to Maṭā‘ and to the holy ones
150 cows and linen vestments and I loaded offerings that I brought from ʾAmḥarā.
If there will be anyone who usurps this gwəlt which I gave
for offering and for commemoration of my beloved Maṭāʿ, may he be excommunicated
by the mouth of the 15 prophets and by the mouth of 12 Apostles, by the mouth of 318 righteous of faith, by the mouth of Ṗeṭros liqa ṗāṗāsāt, by the prayer of the blessed Maṭāʿ and by the mouth of the Father. And the Son and the Holy Spirit may he be excommunicated in this world<pb n="9v"/>and in the world that comes. This [transgression] can not be released through fasting or prayer, begging or bows for ages of ages, Amen.
 I offered this gwəlt and did all this as <persName ref="PRS1854Amdase"><roleName type="title">my lord King
</roleName>ʿĀmda Ṣǝyon </persName> ordered me, saying, 'Go, come to Maṭāʿof ʾAham and do the will of the blessed Maṭāʿ, my beloved. And say: "Do not abandon, o Lord, <persName ref="PRS1854Amdase"><roleName type="title"> my Lord </roleName>ʿĀmda Ṣǝyon </persName>in the days of his youth"'. So I came and cried, wept and rolled myself on the grave of Maṭāʿ as ordered me <persName ref="PRS1854Amdase"><roleName type="title"><sic>my lord
</sic></roleName>ʿĀmda Ṣǝyon. </persName> 'Do for him, o Lord, according to the desire of his heart, saying "Give ʾƎnqarʿo and <placeName ref="LOC3198Galaba">Galabā</placeName>, so that God give me in return for this little a lot in the Heavenly Kingdom, amen." May God give hime in return of a litle - great, amen. May God give him in return for that on the earth - that on the heaven, amen. In return for what ages - what does not age, amen. In return perished - what does not perish, amen. And may He prolong his days on the earth, amen. And may He subdue his rival <pb n="10r"/> and his enemies, amen.
And may he forgive his sins and obliterate the book of his debts, amen. May God give him wisdom as to Solomon, amen. May God give him benevolence as to Dāwit, amen. May God give him patience as to ʾƎyob, amen.  May God give him victory as to ʾIyāsu, amen.
</seg>
<note>Roger Schneider's translator, as he used the edited text by Conti Rossini, translated
  በ፭፻፡ወ፯፡ዓመተ፡ምሕረት, what I translate as 'In the 507th year of Mercy' as 'In the Year of Mercy 506.'
in ስዩመ፡ዘሬዳ the translator interprets ዘ as an element to express a genitive case relationship:
thus, what I translate as 'sǝyum of Zaredā Zarʾa Dāwit' he translates as 'the governor of Redā'.
ኢትንሥኦ፡እግዚኦ፡በመዋዕለ፡ውርዙቱ፡ለእግዚእየ፡ዐምደ፡ጽዮን, which I translate as 'Do not abandon, o Lord, my Lord ʿĀmda Ṣǝyon in the days of his youth' he translates as 'Do not abandor my lord ʿĀmda Ṣǝyon in the days of his youth'.
There are other cases, which should be rather discussed for my choice is dubious:
  ከመ፡ይትወኀሰኒ, which I tranlate as 'would beseech a reward for me', he translates as 'may be my guarantor'; ዘኢይበኦ, which I translate as 'should not penestrate' he translates more literally (may be correctly)'shall enter';
  ኢዘነገሠ፡ወኢዘአንገስገሰ, which I translate as 'neither the one who reigns nor who is agitated' he translates as 'neither the one who is made king nor the one who made king';
  <sic>ቃል፡</sic>ነጋሲ፡ወኢደቀ፡ጽርኅ, which I translate as 'neither the spokesman of nǝguś, nor children of the palace' he translates as 'neither the proxy of the king nor the pages (I am not sure about my interpretation for it makes little sense for me) of the palace';
  ወለእመቦ፡ዘተአገለ, which I traslate as 'if there is anyone who frauds' he translates as 'if there be anyone who transgresses';
  ወመባእሂ፡ጽዒንየ፡ዘአውረድኩ፡በአምኀራ, which I translates as ' I loaded offerings that I brought from ʾAmḥarā' he translates as 'and offerings which I brought down through Amhara on pack animals (marked with a question-mark by a translator himself)';
  ዘኢይትፈታሕ, which I translate as 'This [transgression] can not be released' he translates as 'in such a way that it cannot be revoked';
</note>
</ab>
</div>
</div>
<div type="edition"  xml:lang="gez" corresp="#p2_i5">
<div type="textpart" subtype="folio" n="10r">
  <ab>
ወለይእቲኒ፡<persName ref="PRS2633BelenSa">ብሌን፡ሰባ፡<roleName type="title">በዐልተ፡ቢሐት፡</roleName></persName>የሀባ፡እግዚኣብሔር፡ፍቅረ፡ምስለ፡<persName ref="PRS1854Amdase"><roleName type="function">ምታ፡</roleName>ዐምደ፡ጽዮን፡</persName>ዘገብረት፡ፈቃዶ፡በመልእክናሃ፡በከመ፡ገብር፡ብፁዕ፡ኄር፡ዘያስተፈሥሕ፡እግዚኡ፡በመልእክቱ፡ከማሁ፡ሠናየ፡ገብረት፡በመልእክታ፡የሀባ፡እግዚኣብሔር፡ዕሴተ፡ሠናየ፡አሜን።የሀባ፡እግዚኣብሔር፡መዋዕለ፡ብዙኅ፡በፍሥሐ፡ዘአልቦ፡ሐዘነ፡ምስለ፡<persName ref="PRS1854Amdase"><roleName type="function">ምታ፡</roleName>ዐምደ፡ጽዮን፡</persName>አሜን።ወአመ፡ዕለተ፡ጽዋዓሆሙ፡ያስምዖሙ፡እግዚኣብሔር፡ቃለ፡ፍሥሓ፡ዘይብል፡ንዑ፡ኀቤየ፡ቡሩካኑ፡ለአቡየ፡ትረሱ፡መንግሥተ፡ዘአስተዳለወ፡ለክሙ፡እምቅድመ፡ዓለም፡አሜን።ወይባርክ፡ውሉዶሙ፡አሜን፡ወያብዝኅ፡ዘርኦሙ፡ከመ፡ኮከበ፡
<pb n="10v"/>ሰማይ፡ወከመ፡ኆጻ፡ባሕር፡አሜን፡ወአሜን።
ወይበል፡ኵሉ፡ሕዝብ፡አሜን፡ወአሜን።
</ab>
<note>ብሌን፡ሰባ is ብሌን፡ሳባ in Conti Rossini's edition, ዘገብረት is ዘገብረ.</note>
</div>
</div>
<div type="edition"  xml:lang="en" corresp="#p2_i5">
<div type="textpart" subtype="folio" n="10r">
  <ab>
And for this <persName ref="PRS2633BelenSa">Bǝlen Sabā<roleName type="title">
the lady of Biḥat,</roleName></persName> may God give her love with <persName ref="PRS1854Amdase"><roleName type="function">her husband</roleName>ʿĀmda Ṣǝyon, </persName>who fullfilled his will with her authority, as a good blessed servant that pleases his lord by his service, like this she did good by her service. May God give her good reward, amen. May God give her many days in joy, which do not have sadness, with <persName ref="PRS1854Amdase"><roleName type="function">her husband</roleName>ʿĀmda Ṣǝyon,</persName>amen. And on the day of their summons may God announce them the word of joy saying: 'Come to me blessed by Father, inherit the kingdom, which was prepared for you from before the world, amen.' And may He bless their children, amen and may He multiply their seed like the stars of
<pb n="10v"/>heaven and like the sand of the sea, amen and amen. And let all people say 'Amen and amen'.
</ab>
<note>For ወለይእቲኒ, which I translate as 'And for this', Roger Schneider's translator has 'And to her';
በከመ፡ገብር፡ብፁዕ፡ኄር፡ዘያስተፈሥሕ፡እግዚኡ, which I translate as 'as a good blessed servant that pleases his lord' he translates as 'like a praiseworthy, diligent slave who pleases his master'; በመልእክታ I translate as 'by her service', while he offers 'through her errand'; እምቅድመ፡ዓለም I translate as 'from before the world', he offers 'from the foundation of the world'.</note>
</div>
</div>
<div type="edition"  xml:lang="gez" corresp="#p2_i6">
<div type="textpart" subtype="folio" n="10v">
  <ab>
ወኵልክሙ፡እለ፡አንበብክሙ፡ጸልዩ፡<persName ref="PRS1854Amdase"><roleName type="title">ለንጉሥ፡</roleName>ዐምደ፡ጽዮን፡</persName><persName ref="PRS2633BelenSa"><roleName type="title">ወለንግሥት፡</roleName>ብሌን፡ሰባ፡</persName>ከመ፡ይምሐሮሙ፡እግዚኣብሔር፡በሰማይ፡ወበምድር፡ለዓለመ፡ዓለም፡አሜን፡ወአሜን።
</ab>
<note>Conti Rossini reads ብሌን፡ሰባ as ብሌን፡ሳባ. Transcription by Roger Schneider omits በሰማይ.</note>
</div>
</div>
<div type="edition"  xml:lang="en" corresp="#p2_i6">
<div type="textpart" subtype="folio" n="10v">
  <ab>And all you who read [it], pray for our king ʿĀmda Ṣǝyon and for our quenn Bǝlen Sabā, so that God show mercy on them in heaven and on earth forever and ever, amen and amen.
    </ab>
    </div>
    </div>
<div type="edition"  xml:lang="gez" corresp="#p2_i7" >
<div type="textpart" subtype="folio" n="10v-11r">
<ab>
 <seg ana="#invocation" type="interpretation">በአኰቴተ፡አብ፡ወወልድ፡ወመንፈስ፡ቅዱስ፡</seg>
አነ፡<persName ref="PRS1854Amdase">ዐምደ፡ጽዮን፡</persName>
 ወሀብኩ፡አንፈ፡በዐት፡ማርያም፡ዘሰዐጋ፡ሕፄን፡ይግበሩ፡ሎቱ፡ተዝካሩ፡ለ<add place="overstrike">መጣ</add>ዕ፡ወሊተሂ፡ከመ፡ትዘከረኒ፡እግዚእትየ፡ማርያም፡በጸሎታ፡በኀበ፡ፍቁር፡ወልዳ፡ወዘአጐለትኩ፡በ፭የወ፯፡ዓመተ፡ምሕረት፡አነ፡<persName ref="PRS1854Amdase">ዓምደ፡ጽዮን፡</persName>እንዘ፡<persName ref="PRS2633BelenSa"><title>ሥይምተ፡<placeName ref="LOC2947Endart">እንትርታ፡</placeName></title>ብሌን፡ሰብአ፡</persName>
 እንዘ፡<persName ref="PRS8449Samay"><title>መእከለ፡ባሕር፡</title>ሰማይ፡</persName>
 ወእንዘ፡<persName ref="PRS11566Degna"><title>አውፋሪ፡</title>
 ድግና፡</persName>
 እመቦ፡ዘተሐየለ፡እማርያም፡ዘሰዐጋ፡ <add place="overstrike">አንፈ፡በዓት፡ሕፄን፡</add>ዘወሀብኩ፡አነ፡<persName ref="PRS1854Amdase">ዐምደ፡ጽዮን፡</persName>እመቦ፡
 ዘተሐየሎ፡ወዘተአገሎ፡እመሂ፡ማእከለ፡ባሕር፡ወእመሂ፡ሥዩመ፡እንትርታ፡ወእመሂ፡አውፋሪ፡ወእመሂ፡<sic>ሥዩም፡</sic>አጽቢ፡እመሂ፡ኅዱግ፡<sic>ወቃል፡</sic>ነጋሢ፡ውጉዛን፡ይኩኑ፡አሜን፡በአፈ፡ጴጥሮስ፡ሊቀ፡ጳጳሳት፡አሜን፡በአፈ፡፫፻፡፲ወ፷፡ርቱዓነ፡ሃይማኖት፡አሜን።ወበማርያም፡ወላዲ
 <pb/>ተ፡አምላክ፡ውጉዛነ፡ለይኩኑ፡አሜን።
 </ab>
 <note>Conti Rossini reads ሥይምተ as ሥይመተ, ዘተሐየለ as ዘተሐየሎ, ወዘተአገሎ as ወዘተአገቦ, <sic>ቃል፡</sic>ነጋሢ as ቃለ፡ነጋሢ. Both Conti Rossini and Roger Schneider read my መእከለ፡ባሕር፡ሰማይ as መእከለ፡ባሕር፡ስማይ.
Roger Schneider did three notes not the text:
1.(ሕፄን) The two letters ፄን፡ are smaller and seem to have been written over an erasure.
2.(ለመጣዕ) መጣ has been written later over an erasure.
3.([አንፈ፡በዓት]፡ሕ[ፄን፡])The passages between brackets have been written over an erasure, by a later hand.
</note>
 </div>
 </div>
 <div type="edition"  xml:lang="en" corresp="#p2_i7" >
<div type="textpart" subtype="folio" n="10v-11r">
<ab>
 <seg ana="#invocation" type="interpretation">To the glory of the Father and the Son and the Holy Spirit.</seg>
 I, <persName ref="PRS1854Amdase">ʿĀmda Ṣǝyon </persName>
granted ʾAnfa Baʿat [to] Māryām za-Saʿagā Ḥǝṣen so that they celebrate the commemoration of Maṭāʿ and for me, so that my Lady Mary remember me in her prayer to her beloved Son. It was in 507 year of Mercy that I granted gwǝlt, I,  <persName ref="PRS1854Amdase">ʿĀmda Ṣǝyon, </persName>
while <persName ref="PRS2633BelenSa"><title>sǝyǝmt of <placeName ref="LOC2947Endart">ʾƎntǝrtā</placeName></title>Bǝlen Sabā, </persName>
 while<persName ref="PRS8449Samay"><title>maʾǝkala bāḥr</title>Samāy,</persName>
 and while <persName ref="PRS11566Degna"><title>ʾawfāri</title>
 Dǝgnā.</persName>
 If there is anyone who usurps from Māryām za-Saʿagā ʾAnfa Baʿat Ḥǝṣen, which I,<persName ref="PRS1854Amdase">ʿĀmda Ṣǝyon</persName>granted, if there is anyone who violates or defraudes it, if even maʾǝkala bāḥr or
 sǝyum of ʾƎntǝrtā, if even ʾawfāri or  sǝyum of ʾAṣbi, if even a deputy or a spokesman of nǝgus, may they be excommunicated, amen, by the mouth of
 Ṗeṭros liqa ṗāṗāsāt, amen; by the mouth of 318 righteous of faith, amen. And by Māryām, bearer of
 <pb/>Lord, may they be excommunicated, amen.
</ab>
<note>ወሀብኩ I translate as 'I granted', while Roger Schneider's translator has it as 'I have given'; ይግበሩ፡ሎቱ፡ተዝካሩ I translate as 'they celebrate the commemoration', while he offers 'they [the priests] may celebrate the commemoration'; እንዘ፡<persName ref="PRS8449Samay"><title>መእከለ፡ባሕር፡</title>ሰማይ</persName>, which I interprete as 'while<persName ref="PRS8449Samay"><title>maʾǝkala bāḥr</title>Samāy</persName>', he misinterpreted as '[that of] Maʾǝkala Bāḥr, Semay';
ወዘተአገለ I translate as 'defraudes it', while he has 'transgresses', marking Conti Rossini's 'ወዘተአገቦ' in square brakets with a question mark; እመሂ፡ማእከለ፡ባሕር, which I translate as 'if even maʾǝkala bāḥr', he has misinterpreted again into 'be it the [governor of] Maʾǝkala Bāḥr'; <sic>ወቃል፡</sic>ነጋሢ, which I translate as 'a spokesman of nǝgus', he translates as 'a king's proxy'.
</note>
</div>
</div>
      <div type="edition"  xml:lang="geez" corresp="#p2_8">
      <div type="textpart" subtype="folio" n="11v">
      <ab>
        <seg ana="#invocation" type="interpretation">በአኰቴተ፡አብ፡ወወልደ፡ወመንፈስ፡ቅዱስ፡</seg>
        አግባእኩ፡አነ፡
        <persName ref="PRS6073Krestos">ክርስቶስ፡አቡሁ፡</persName>በአፈ፡<persName ref="PRS1854Amdase">ዐምደ፡ጽዮን፡<title>ንጉሥ፡</title></persName>ተርካ፡ዘቀዳሚ፡ምድሮሙ፡ለቅዱሳን፡እለ፡ቤተ፡መጣዕ፡እንዘ፡ዐቃቤ፡ሰዐት፡ዕቅባ፡እግዚእ፡ወእመ፡ቦ፡ዘተኀየሎሙ፡ወዘተአገሎሙ፡ለቅዱሳን፡ይእቲ፡ምድር፡በጽንፋ፡ወበቀልቀላ፡ለተርካ፡ውጉዘ፡ለይኩን፡በቅድመ፡አብ፡ወወልድ፡ወመንፈስ፡ቅዱስ፡በአ
        <cb/>
ፈ፡፫፻፡፲ወ፷፡ርቱዐነ፡ሃይማኖት፡ወበአፈ፡፲ወ፭፡ነቢያት፡ወበአፈ፡፲ወ፪፡ሐዋርያት፡ወበአፈ፡ጴጥሮስ፡ሊቀ፡ጳጳሳት፡ዘኢይትፈታሕ፡በጾም፡ወበጸሎት፡በስኢል፡ወበሰጊድ፡ለዓለመ፡ዓለም፡አሜን፡ወአሜን፡ለይኩን፡ለይኩን።ወእመቦ፡ዘደምሰሳ፡ወዘቀደዳ፡በጽልሑት፡ከማሁ፡ለይኩን፡ውጉዘ፡ለዓለመ፡ዓለም፡አሜን።
<note>በቅድመ፡አብ Conti Rossini has as በአፈ፡አብ.
  Roger Schneider had one comment to this text:
  1.ዐቃቤ፡ሰዓት has been erased, but the letters are still faintly discernible. The copy B still has it.
</note>
  </ab>
        </div>
        </div>
        <div type="edition"  xml:lang="en" >
        <div type="textpart" subtype="folio" n="11v">
        <ab>
          <seg ana="#invocation" type="interpretation">To the glory of the Father and the Son and the Holy Spirit.</seg>
          I, <persName ref="PRS6073Krestos">Krǝstos ʾAbuhu,</persName>restored, by the mouth of<persName ref="PRS1854Amdase">King ʿĀmda Ṣǝyon,</persName>
          Tarkā, previously the land of the holy ones of the church of Maṭāʿ,
          while ʿaqābe saʿat ʿƎqbā ʾƎgziʾ. And if there is anyone who would violate or pervert from the holy ones this land, [even] on the borders or cliffs of Tarkā, may he be excommunicated in front of the Father  and the Son and the Holy Spirit by the mouth
          <cb/>
          of 318 righteous in faith and by the mouth of 15 prophets and by the mouth of 12 apostles and by the mouth of Ṗeṭros liqa ṗāṗāsāt, that will not be forgiven through fasting or prayer, through vows or bows unto the ages of ages, amen and amen. May it be so, may it be so. And if there is anyone who
          erase it or who scratch it in deceit, may he be likewise excommunicated unto the ages of ages, amen.
<note>Roger Schneider's translator offers 'have brough in' for አግባእኩ, which I translate as 'restored'; ወእመ፡ቦ፡ዘተኀየሎሙ፡ወዘተአገሎሙ he has as 'if there is anyone who snaches or usurps', which I translate as 'would violate or pervert'; በጽንፋ፡ወበቀልቀላ he translates as 'on the edges and slopes', while I translate as 'on the borders or cliffs'; በቅድመ፡አብ, which I translate as 'in front of the Father', he has as 'by the mouth of the Father', which shows that he was translating from Conti Rossini's edition.
 ዘኢይትፈታሕ, which I translates as 'that will not be forgiven', he translates as 'which [excommunication] will not be revoked'; ወእመቦ፡ዘደምሰሳ፡ወዘቀደዳ፡በጽልሑት I translate as 'if there is anyone who
 erase it or who scratch it in deceit', while he translates it as 'if there is anyone who with a bad intention erases or tears it'.</note>
    </ab>
              </div>
              </div>
              <div type="edition"  xml:lang="geez" corresp="#p3_i1">
              <div type="textpart" subtype="folio" n="12r">
              <ab>
                በአኰቴተ፡አብ፡ወወልድ፡ወመንፈስ፡ቅዱስ:ጸሐፍነ፡ኀቢረነ፡ወሠሚረነ፡ተጋቢአነ፡ቅዱሳን፡ዐቃቤ፡ሰዓት፡ዘቤተ፡መጣዕ፡ከመ፡ኢያውፅኡ፡አልባሰ፡ዘመጣዕ፡ኢዐቢየ፡ወኢንኡሰ፡ወኢየሀቡ፡ለቤተ፡<subst><del rend="erasure"/><add place="overstrike">መጣዕ፡<unclear/></add></subst>ወለእመቦ፡ዘወሀበ፡ለመርዓ፡እምነ፡አልባስ፡ዘአባ፡መጣዕ፡እመሂ፡፩
                <unclear/>ወእመሂ፡ቀይሰ፡ገበዝ፡ወእመሂ፡መነኮሳት፡እመሂ፡ዓቢይ፡ወእመሂ፡ንኡስ፡እመሂ፡ሥዩም፡ወእመሂ፡ሥዑር፡ለእመቦ፡ዘአውፅአ፡<cb/>
      <unclear/>በቅድመ፡አብ፡ወወልድ፡ወመንፈስ፡ቅዱስ፡ለዓለመ፡ዓለም፡አሜን፡ወአሜን፡ለይኩን፡ለይኩን፡አሜን።
                </ab>
                </div>
                </div>

              <div type="edition"  xml:lang="geez" corresp="#p4_i1">
              <div type="textpart" subtype="folio" n="13r">
              <ab>
                  <seg ana="#invocation" type="interpretation"> በአኰቴተ፡አብ፡ወወልድ፡ወመንፈስ፡ቅዱስ:</seg>
              ዘወሀቡ፡ቀደምት፡ተርከ፡ለአቡነ፡ሊባኖስ፡ወአነሂ፡ተንሥአ፡ክርስቶስ፡ወሀብኩ፡ወአግባእኩ፡ዘተገፍዐ፡ተርከ፡አነ፡<del rend="effaced"/>
    ከመ፡ይትወሐሠኒ፡መጣዕ፡በመንግሥተ፡ሰማያት፡ከመ፡ይግበሩ፡ተዝከርየ፡ደቂቀ፡መካን፡ወኢይርስዑኒ፡በጊዜ፡ጸሎት፡ሰሚዕየ፡ዘይቤ፡ቃለ፡ሰሎሞን፡መክብብ፡ከንቱ፡ከንቱ፡ለዓለም፡ንብረ<cb/>
    ቱ፡ዘእንበለ፡ዘገብረ፡ሥንቁ፡በመዋዕለ፡ሕይወቱ፡የሀቦ፡እግዚአብሔር፡ለተንሥአ፡ክርስቶስ፡<del rend="effaced"/>
    መንግሥተ፡ሰማያት፡ህየንተ፡ኅዳጥ፡ብዙኅ፡አሜን፡የሀቦ፡እግዚአብሔር፡ህየንተ፡ንስቲት፡ዓቢይ፡የሀቦ፡እግዚአብሔር፡ህየንተ፡ዘቦ፡ምድር፡ዘበ፡ሰማያት፡ወያኑኅ፡መዋዕሊሁ፡በዲበ፡ምድር፡ወያግርር፡ፀሮ፡ወጸላእቶ፡አሜን።ወይስረይ፡ኃጢአተ፡ወይደምሰስ፡መጽሐ
    <handShift/>ፈ፡ዕዳሁ፡አሜን።ወለእመቦ፡ዘሄዳ፡ወዘተአገላ፡ውጉዘ፡ለይኩን፡ዘኢይትፈታሕ፡በጾም፡ወበጸሎት፡በአፉሁ፡ለአቡነ፡መጣዕ፡አሜን።

                </ab>
                </div>
                </div>
                <div type="edition"  xml:lang="en" corresp="#p4_i1">
                <div type="textpart" subtype="folio" n="13r">
                <ab>
                    <seg ana="#invocation" type="interpretation">To the glory of the Father and the Son and the Holy Spirit.</seg>
                  </ab>
                  </div>
                  </div>

                <div type="edition"  xml:lang="geez" corresp="#p4_i2">
                <div type="textpart" subtype="folio" n="13vb">
                <ab>
                ወሀብኩ፡አነ፡ይሥምከ፡እግዚእ፡ሥዩመ፡ኀማሳን፡ለአባ፡መጣዕ፡ዘአሀም፡ፈዋሴ፡ዱያን፡ኀበ፡ተቀብረ፡አዕጽምቲሁ፡፭፡ነፍሰ፡ሰብእ፡ገድቦ፡ምስለ፡ብእሲቱ፡ወደቂቁ፡ከመ፡ይትወሐሰኒ፡መጣዕ፡በመንግሥተ፡ሰማያት፡ወያኑኅ፡መዋዕልየ፡በዲበ፡ምድር፡ወይዕቀብ፡ነፍስየ፡ወሥጋየ፡ምስለ፡አንስትያየ፡ወደቂቅየ፡ወዘመድየ፡ወበቀዳሚ፡ወሀብኩ፡መንጦላዕተ፡በርኴናየት፡እስመ፡ስማዕኩ፡ቃለ፡መክብብ፡ዘይቤ፡ኵሉ፡ከንቱ፡ከንቱ፡ውእቱ፡ዘኢገብረ፡ሠናየ፡በሕይወቱ።ወበዐጋማሂ፡አር5ዕኩ፡ጕልተ።
                  </ab>
                  </div>
                  </div>
     <div type="edition"  xml:lang="geez" corresp="#p5_i1">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="folio" n="14r">
<ab>
  <pb n="14r"/>
 ወእንዘ፡ሀለዉ፡ክልኤሆሙ፡ኅቡረ፡<persName ref="PRS6152Lalibala">ላሊበላ፡<roleName type="title">ንጉሥ፡</roleName></persName>ወ<persName ref="PRS6859MasqalK"><roleName type="function">ብእሲቱ፡</roleName>መስቀል፡ክብራ፡<roleName type="title">በአልተ፡ቢሐት፡</roleName></persName>ከመ፡ይኩኖሙ፡መድኀኒተ፡ነፍሶሙ፡በመንግሥተ፡ሰማያት፡ወለብእሲትየኒ፡ከመ፡ይደምራ፡ምስለ፡ቅድ
ሳት፡ምስለ፡ሳራ፡ወሰራሜ፡ምስለ፡ሐና፡ወሶፍያ፡ወኢይዝክር፡ላቲ፡ኀጢአታ፡ወይደምስስ፡መጸሐፈ፡ጌጋያ፡አሜን።ወአሜን።ለይኩን፡ለይኩን።ወእንዘ፡ሀለዉ፡ዓበይተ፡<placeName ref="LOC2002Bugna">܆ብጕና፡</placeName>
<persName ref="PRS12848Abt"><roleName type="title">ቃለጳስ፡</roleName>አብት፡</persName>
<persName ref="PRS11336Giyorgis"><roleName type="title">ጳጳስ፡</roleName>አባ፡ጊዮርጊስ፡</persName>
<persName ref="PRS5107Harayo"><roleName type="title">ወኤጲስ፡ቆጶስ፡</roleName>ኀረዮ፡</persName>
<persName ref="PRS10332Yerdea"><roleName type="title">ዓቃቤ፡ሰዓት፡መጣዕ፡</roleName>ይርድአነ፡ክርስቶስ፡</persName>
<persName ref="PRS12836Sawen"><roleName type="title">ሊቀ፡ዲያቆናት፡</roleName>ሰውን፡</persName>
<persName ref="PRS12837AbYekun"><roleName type="title">ቀይሰ፡ገበዝ፡ጽዮን፡</roleName>አብ፡ይኩን፡</persName>
<persName ref="PRS12838Yetbarak"><roleName type="title">መልሐዘ፡</roleName>ይትባረክ፡</persName>
<persName ref="PRS12839ZaAdonay"><roleName type="title">ቀስ፡ሐጺን፡</roleName>ዘአዶናየ፡</persName>
<persName ref="PRS12840KrestosBen"><roleName type="title">ጸዋር፡ናርጌ፡መኣሰሬ፡</roleName>ክርስቶስ፡ብነ፡</persName>
<persName ref="PRS12841Sebhat"><roleName type="title">ጸሐፍ፡ላም፡</roleName>ስብሐት፡</persName>
<persName ref="PRS12842Yeqbeena"><roleName type="title">ሐስጓ፡</roleName>ይዕቀበነ፡</persName>
<persName ref="PRS12844Asgada"><roleName type="title">ማእከለ፡ባሕር፡</roleName>ኣስገደ፡</persName>
<persName ref="PRS12843BaraSeyon"><roleName type="title">ዓቃ፡ጸንጸን፡</roleName>ባራ፡ጽዮን፡</persName>
<persName ref="PRS12845Yemheranna"><roleName type="title">ዐቃብ፡ደጌ፡ማሰረይ፡</roleName>ይምሐረነ፡</persName>
<persName ref="PRS12846Zarawedem"><roleName type="title">ሊቀ፡አቀይታት፡</roleName>ዘረውድም፡</persName>
እንዘ፡
<persName ref="PRS12847ZaAmalay"><roleName type="title">ሊቀ፡ኬኖት፡</roleName>ዘአመላይ፡</persName>
ወእንዘ፡
<persName ref="PRS12848Yamo"><roleName type="title">ሊቀ፡ኅዳር፡</roleName>ያሞ፡</persName>
<persName ref="PRS12849WaldaBegwenay"><roleName type="title">ሊቀ፡መሰንቆ፡</roleName>ወልደ፡ብጕናይ፡</persName>
ወከመዝ፡ኣጐላትኩ፡ዘኣልቦ፡ግብረ፡ወገብጋበ፡መፍቀሬ፡እግዚአብሔር፡ዘወሀበ፡<persName ref="PRS6152Lalibala">ላሊበላ፡</persName>ዘንተ፡ጕልተ፡ዘገፍዓ፡ውጉዘ፡ለይኩን፡አሜን፡ዘንተ፡ዘአጽሐፈ፡
<persName ref="PRS10332Yerdea"><roleName type="title">ዐቃቤ፡ስዐተ፡መጣዕ፡</roleName>ስመ፡ልደቱ፡ይርድአነ፡ክርስቶስ፡ከመ፡ምንኵስናሁ፡ጸጋ፡መጣዕ፡</persName>
ለዘአጽሐፈ፡ወለዘጸሐፈ፡ስረዩ፡ወባርኩነ፡ኣሜን።
</ab>
</div>
</div>
<div type="edition" xml:lang="en" corresp="#p5_i1">
<div type="textpart" subtype="folio" n="14r">
<ab>
<pb n="14r"/>
And while two were united, <persName ref="PRS6152Lalibala"><roleName type="title">King</roleName>Lālibālā</persName>and<persName ref="PRS6859MasqalK"><roleName type="function">his wife</roleName>Masqal Kǝbra<roleName type="title">baʾalt of Biḥat,
</roleName></persName> so that it become salvation of their souls in the Heavenly Kingdom, and for my wife may it associate her with saint women, with Sārā and Salome, with Ḥānnā and Sofiā and may He not remember her sin and may the book of her transgressions be obliterated, Amen and Amen.Let it be, let it be.
And while the greats of<placeName ref="LOC2002Bugna">Bǝgwǝna</placeName> were
<persName ref="PRS12848Abt"><roleName type="title">qālaṗās</roleName>Abt,</persName>
<persName ref="PRS11336Giyorgis"><roleName type="title">pāpās</roleName><roleName type="title">ʾabuna</roleName>Giyorgis</persName>
and<persName ref="PRS5107Harayo"><roleName type="title">ʾeṗisqoṗos </roleName>Ḫarayo,</persName>
<persName ref="PRS10332Yerdea"><roleName type="title">ʿāqābe saʿāt Maṭāʿ</roleName>Yǝrdǝʾanna Krǝstos,</persName>
<persName ref="PRS12836Sawen"><roleName type="title">liqa diyāqonāt</roleName>Sawǝn,</persName>
<persName ref="PRS12837AbYekun"><roleName type="title">qaysa gabaz Ṣǝyon</roleName>ʾAb Yǝkun,</persName>
<persName ref="PRS12838Yetbarak"><roleName type="title">malḥaza</roleName>Yǝtbārak,</persName>
<persName ref="PRS12839ZaAdonay"><roleName type="title">qas ḥaṣin</roleName>Za-’Adonāya,</persName>
<persName ref="PRS12840KrestosBena"><roleName type="title">ṣawar nārge ma’āsare</roleName>Krǝstos Bǝna,</persName>
<persName ref="PRS12841Sebhat"><roleName type="title">ṣaḥaf lām</roleName>Sǝbḥat,</persName>
<persName ref="PRS12842Yeqbeena"><roleName type="title">ḥasgwā</roleName>Yǝ‘ǝqabanna,</persName>
<persName ref="PRS12844Asgada"><roleName type="title">mā’ǝkala bāḥr</roleName>ʾAsgada,</persName>
<persName ref="PRS12843BaraSeyon"><roleName type="title">‘aqā ṣanṣan</roleName>Bārā Ṣeyon,</persName>
<persName ref="PRS12845Yemheranna"><roleName type="title">‘aqāb dage māsaray</roleName>Yǝmḥaranna,</persName>
<persName ref="PRS12846Zarawedem"><roleName type="title">liqa ’aqqaytāt</roleName>Zara Wǝdǝm,</persName>
while
<persName ref="PRS12847ZaAmalay"><roleName type="title">liqa kenot</roleName>Za-ʾAmalāy</persName>
and while
<persName ref="PRS12848Yamo"><roleName type="title">liqa ḫǝdār</roleName>Yāmo,</persName>
<persName ref="PRS12849WaldaBegwenay"><roleName type="title">liqa masanqo</roleName>Walda Bǝgwǝnāy.</persName>
Thus at that time I promoted this gwǝlt given by <persName ref="PRS6152Lalibala">Lālibālā</persName>, lover of God, without taxation or forced labour; who will restrain this gwǝlt, shall that one be excommunicated, Amen.
This was written upon the request of <persName ref="PRS10332Yerdea"><roleName type="title">ʿāqābe saʿāt Maṭāʿ,</roleName> [named] at birth Yǝrdǝʾanna Krǝstos and  at entering monkhood as Ṣaggā Maṭāʿ.</persName> Relent that one who requested to write [this] and that one who wrote [this] and bless us, Amen.
</ab>
</div>
</div>
<div type="edition" xml:lang="geez" corresp="#p5_i2">
<div type="textpart"  subtype="folio" n="14v" xml:lang="geez">
<ab>
<pb n="14v"/>
<seg ana="#inovacation" type="interpretation">በአኰቴተ፡አብ፡ወወልድ፡ወመንፈስ፡ቅዱስ።</seg>
<seg ana="#suscription" type="interpretation">ወሀብኩ፡አነ፡<persName ref="PRS10332Yerdea">ይርድአነ፡ክርስቶስ፡ብጕናይ፡ዘጽላላ፡<roleName type="title">ዐቃቤ፡ሰዐተ፡መጣዕ፡</roleName></persName></seg>
<seg ana="#provision" type="interpretation">ገራውሀ፡በቢሓት፡፴፪፡ከመ፡ይትወሰኒ፡መጣዕ፡በመንግሥተ፡ሰማያት፡ወሀብኩ፡ለመጣዕ፡ለመባእ፡ዘዋህበኒ፡በዐለ፡ምድራ፡ሠሚሮ፡ወፈቲዎ፡ወልደ፡ማእከሊ፡ዘእመረ፡ዘአልቦ፡ዘተአገሎ፡ዘተኀየሎ፡ለመጣዕ፡እመሂ፡ሥዩም፡ወእመሂ፡ስዑር፡ውጉዘ፡ለይኩን፡በዝ፡ዓለም፡ወበዘ፡ይመጽእ፡ዓለም፡ውጉዘ፡ለይኩን፡በአፉሁ፡ለአቡነ፡መጣዕ፡ወበአፈ፡ኢየሱስ፡ክርስቶስ፡አሜን።ይኩን፡ለይኩን። ። ።
</seg>
  </ab>
  </div>
  </div>
  <div type="edition" xml:lang="en" corresp="#p5_i2">
  <div type="textpart" corresp="#p2_i2" subtype="folio" n="14v" xml:lang="en">
  <ab>
  <pb n="14v"/>
  <seg ana="#inovacation" type="interpretation">To the glory of the Father and the Son and the Holy Spirit,</seg>
<seg ana="#suscription" type="interpretation">I, <persName ref="PRS10332Yerdea">Yǝrdǝʾanna Krǝstos of Bəgwənāy of Ṣəlālā, <roleName type="title">‘aqābe sa‘āta Maṭā‘</roleName></persName>gave</seg>
<seg ana="#provision" type="interpretation">thirty two fields of Biḥāt, to be granted by Maṭā‘ in the Heavenly Kingdom. I gave to Maṭā‘ as a donation what Walda Ma’əkali, the lord of the land, gave me agreeing and willing, who knows that what I took was not by force or violence. If someone would violate or defraud Maṭā‘, whether appointed or whether displaced, be excommunicated, in this world and in the coming world, by the mouth of Maṭā‘ and by the mouth of Jesus Christ. Amen. Let it be, let it be.</seg>
  </ab>
  </div>
  </div>
  <div type="edition" xml:lang="geez" corresp="#p6_i1">
<div type="textpart" subtype="folio" n="15r">
<ab>
  በስመ፡አብ፡ወወል/ድ/፡ወመን/ፈስ፡ቅዱስ፡/አነ፡ተከሥተ፡ብ//፡ነብር፡እደ፡ሰዐት፡ዘመጣዕ፧//ኩ፡ለመጣዕ፡//ባአ፡፫፡ገራህተ፡//ገራህተ፡በ//፡ሚካslኤል፡ወገ//ህተ፡ ///ዖነ፡ትሕተ፡መን፡ክምል፡ዐቀባ፡ድ፡ቅስዳድ፡በቢሐት፡//ይበጽሕ፡ለመነኮሳት፡መጣዕ፡ወለዐቃቤ፡ሰዐት፡ከመ፡ይትወሐሰኒ፡መጣዕ፡በመንግሥተ፡ሰማያት፡እንዘ፡ሀለዉ፡መነኮሳተ፡መጣዕ፡ቤቤተ፡ጽርሕ፡እንዘ፡ንጉሥ፡ይኩናት፡ወእንዘ፡ሊቀ፡ጳጳሳት፡አባ፡ቄርሎስ፡ወእንዘ፡ሥዩም፡እን//ታ፡እንግዳ፡እግዚእ፡ወእንዘ፡ሥዩም፡ደብረ፡ማዕፆ፡ኅራሳይ፡እመቦ፡ዘተኀየሎ፡ወእመቦ፡ዘተአገሎ፡ውጉዘ፡ለይኩን፡በአሊሁ፡ለመጣዕ፡ወበአፈ፡ኵሎሙ፡ቅዱሳን፡በ፩፻//፩፡ዓመተ፡ምሕረት፡ለዓለመ፡ዓለም፡አሜን፡ወአሜን።///// lb
  </ab>
  </div>
  </div>
  <div type="edition" xml:lang="geez" corresp="#p6_i2">
<div type="textpart" subtype="folio" n="15r">
<ab>
  non reperibile in CCR
  </ab>
  </div>
  </div>
  <div type="edition" xml:lang="geez" corresp="#p6_i3">
<div type="textpart" subtype="folio" n="15v">
<ab>
  በአኰቴተ፡ ///////ብ፡ወወልድ፡ወመንፈስ፧/////////
ወሀብኩ፡ለቤተ፡መስቀል፡ወለቤተ፡ማርያም፡ወለደናል፡ከመ፡ይምሐረኒ፡እግዚአ፡ብሔር፡በጸሎቶሙ።ወሀብኩ፡አነሂ፡በከመ፡ወሀቡ፡ነገሥት፡ሠጦ፡ምድረ፡አላፎ።ወዴር፡ወዐድ፡ልጋት፡ወማዕጠውሎ፡ወምካምስ፡ወምድረ፡መስተፋ፡ምስለ፡ሰርሓ፡ወዐድ፡ዳዕሮ፡አግባእኩ፡አነ፡ንጉሥ፡ይኵኖ፡አምላክ፡እንዘ፡ማእከለ፡ባሕር፡ያግባጽዮን፡እንዘ፡ሥዩመ፡እንትርታ፡ወዐቃቤ፡ጸንጸን፡ወኃሥጓ፡አነ፡እንግዳ፡እግዚእ፡ወልደ፡ኵሉ፡ሰገደ።ወእንዘ፡ንቡረ፡እድ፡ዘአክሱም፡ወዐቃቤ፡ሰዓት፡ዘቤተ፡መጣዕ፡ተከሥተ፡ብርሃን።ወእንዘ፡በዐልተ፡መካን፡ቅድስት፡ማርያም፡ዘአግበአ፡ዘንተ፡ጕልተ፡የሀቦ፡እግዚአብሔር፡መንግሥተ፡ሰማያት፡ወይደምሮ፡ምስለ፡ቅዱሳን፡ወሰማዕት፡ወያኑ/፡መዋዕሊሁ፡በዲበ፡ምድር፡ወይዕቀብ፡ነፍሶ፡ወብእሲቶ፡ወውሉዶ፡ወሰራዊቶ፡ለዓለመ፡ዓለም፡አሜን፡ወአሜን፡ለይኩን፡ለይኩን፡እመቦ፡ዘተኀየለ፡ወዘተአገለ፡ዘንተ፡ጕ///፡ውጉዘ፡ለይኵን፡በቅድመ፡አብ፡ወወልድ፡ወመንፈስ፡ቅዱስ፡በሰማይ፡ወበምድር፡በአ/፡፲ወ፭፡ነቢያት፡በአፈ፡፲ወ፪፡ሐዋርያት፡ወ///ርድ////በአፈ፡፫፻፡ወ፰፡ርቱዓነ፡////ለዓለም፡አሜን። ። pb
  </ab>
  </div>
  </div>
  <div type="edition" xml:lang="geez" corresp="#p7_i1">
<div type="textpart" subtype="folio" n="16r-17v">
<ab>
  <pb n="16r"/><cb n="a"/>
           <seg ana="#invocation" type="interpretation">በአኰቴተ፡አብ፡ወወልድ፡ወመንፈስ፡ቅዱስ፡</seg>
            <seg ana="#subscription" type="interpretation">አጽሐፍኩ፡አነ፡
<subst> <del rend="erasure"/><add place="overstrike">ገብረ፡መስቀል፡</add></subst>ንጉሥ።በ፭፻፲ወ፪።ዓመተ፡ምሕረት፡አጕለትኩ፡አነ፡
<subst> <del rend="erasure"/><add place="overstrike">ገብረ፡መስቀል፡ንጉሥ፡ወስመ፡መንግሥትየ፡ሰሎሞን፡ወአክሰምኩ፡ዘንተ፡ጕልተ፡ለአባ፡መጣዕ፡ዘውእቱ፡ሊባኖስ፡
</add></subst></seg>
<seg ana="#provision" type="interpretation">ወአነሂ፡ወሀብኩ፡በእንተ፡ፍቅሩ፡ለመጣዕ፡ከመ፡ይትወሐስኒ፡በመንገሥተ፡ሰማያት።ወያኑኅ፡መዋዕልየ፡በዲበ፡ምድር፡አግባእኩ፡ዘንተ፡ጕልተ፡በአዌካር፡፭፡ዓ<cb n="b"/>
ድ፡ሕፄን፡ወእላንታ፡ቢሐት፡ወእንቀርዖ፡ቀርንኦም፡ምሕባኣ፡መንደልት፡ወምጕልብታ፡ገለባ፡ወሴሴት፡በድዕዱዕ፡፯፡ዐድ፡በመረገኒያ፡፯፡ዐድ፡ተዲረር፡ዐጋሚ፡ምስለ፡ምድሮሙ፡በኀበ፡ሀለዉ፡ወርቅ፡ወአልባስ፡፫፻፡ወ፵፡ክቡራት፡ወለቅዱሳን፡፵፡ብዙት፡ወ፲፻፡ላህም፡፳፡መነሳንስት፡፭፡ስራዌልየ፡አውጻእየ፡እምሐቋይ፡ወ፭፡አሣእንየ፡አውጺእየ፡እምእገርየ።<lb/><space></space>
ወሀብኩ፡ለመጣዕ፡ወ፭፡መስቀል፡ዘወርቅ፡ወ፩፡ጻሕል፡
<pb n="16v"/><cb n="a"/>
ዘወርቅ፡ወ፩፡ጽዋዕ፡ዘወርቅ፡፩፡ጽዋዕ፡ዘብሩር።ወክልኤቱ፡ጻሕል፡ዘድዕም፡መብራህት፡ወዕጣን፡ዘአልቦ፡ኆልቈ።<lb/><space></space>
ወለካልአን፡ቤተ፡ክርስቲያናት፡እለ፡ውስተ፡ሀገሩ፡፴፡አልባስ፡ክቡራት።ወዘንተ፡ኵሎ፡ዘወሀብኩ፡አነ፡<subst> <del rend="erasure"/><add place="overstrike">ገብረ፡መስቀል፡</add></subst>ንጉሥ፡
አእሚርየ፡ከመ፡የሐልፍ፡ኵሎ፡ንብረተ፡ዝንቱ፡ዓለም፡ወሰማዕኩ፡ቃለ፡መክብብ፡ዘይቤ፡ከንቱ፡ኵሉ፡ከንቱ፡ዘእንበለ፡ዘአቅደመ፡ስንቆ፡በሒይወቱ፡
<space></space>
<cb n="b"/>
ወሀብኩ፡አነ፡ክርስቶስ፡ኣቡሁ፡ለመጣዕ፡ዘአሃም፡ዘአዘዘኒ፡እግዚእየ፡<del rend="erasure"></del>እንዘ፡ሥዩመ፡እንትርታ።
ወእንዘ፡መእከለ፡ባሕር፡እንዘ፡ማእከለ፡ትዋዛት።
ወእንዘ፡ሐስጓ፡ወዐቃንጻን።ባሕረ፡ሰገድ፡ወልዱ፡<del rend="erasure"></del>ለንጉሥ።<lb/><space></space>
ወበታሕቴሁ፡ክርስቶስ፡አቡሁ፡መኰንን።<lb/><space></space>
እ<add place="above">ን</add>ዘ፡ሕ<unclear/>
ሠናይት፡አይሶ፡እንዘ፡መአሰሬ፡ንጉሥ፡ካሕሱ፡ወልደ፡ኖላዊ።<lb/><space></space>
ወእንዘ፡ ዓቃቤ፡
<pb n="17r"/><cb n="a"/>
ሰዓተ፡መጣዕ፡ገብረ፡ክርስቶስ፡ወልዱ፡ለበርናባስ።ዘአጽሐፍዋ፡ተጋቢኦሙ፡በሕዘእተ፡ምስያም።አመ፡ይሁቦ፡እግዚአብሔር፡ለ<subst> <del rend="erasure"/><add place="overstrike">ገብረ፡መስቀል፡</add></subst> ምድረ፡በምልኣ።<lb/><space></space>
ወዘንተ፡ኵሎ፡ጕልተ፡ዘ<subst> <del rend="erasure"/><add place="overstrike">አጐለት</add></subst>ኩ፡ለአቡነ፡መጣዕ።
ዘኢይበውኦ፡ሥዩም፡ዘኢስዑር፡ኢመኰንን፡ወኢሐያል፡ወኢቃለ፡ነጋሢ።<lb/><space></space>
ኢአንበሳ፡ወኢፈረስ፡ኢማእከለ፡ባሕር።<lb/><space></space>
ወኢአውፋሪ፡ኢኣፈ፡አውፋሪ።<lb/><space></space>
ኢሥዩመ፡አዌገ<cb n="b"/>ር፡ወኢገዘአ፡አዌገር።ኢሥዩመ፡ደብረ፡መዕጾ፡ወኢሕዱጉ።<lb/><space></space>
ኢሥዩመ፡ዘሬዳ፡ወኢገዛአ፡ዘሬዳ።
ኢአውፈሪ፡ሐማሴን፡ኢዐቃንጻን፡ሐማሴን።<lb/><space></space>
ዘኢይበውኦ፡ለመረገንያ፡ወለድዕዱዕ፡<subst><del rend="erasure"/><add place="overstrike">ሕፄን፡</add></subst>ጕልቱ፡ለመጣዕ፡ዘአሀም፡ዘወሀብኩ፡አነ፡<subst><del rend="erasure"/><add place="overstrike">ሰሎሞን፡</add></subst>ንጉሥ።<lb/><space></space>
ወለእመቦ፡ዘተሐየሎ፡ወዘተአገሎ፡ውጉዘ፡ለይኩን፡በአፈ፡፲፭፡ነቢያት፡ወበአፈ፡፲ወ፪፡ሐዋርያት፡በአፈ፡፳ወ፬፡ካህናተ፡ሰማይ።በአፈ፡፫፻፲ወ፰፡<pb/>ርቱዓነ፡ሀይማኖት፡ወበአፈ፡ጴጥሮስ፡ሊቀ፡ጳጳሳት፡ወበጸሎቱ፡ለብፁዕ፡መጣዕ።<lb/><space></space>
ወበአፈ፡አብ፡ወወልድ፡ወመንፈስ፡ቅዱስ፡ውጉዘ፡ለይኩን፡በዝ፡ዓለም፡ወበዘይመጽእ፡ዓለም፡ዘኢይትፈተሕ፡በጾም፡ወበጸሎት፡በስኢል፡ወበሰጊድ፡ለዓለመ፡ዓለም፡አሜን።<lb/><space></space></seg>
</ab>
</div>
</div>
<div type="edition" xml:lang="en" corresp="#p7_i1">
<div type="textpart" subtype="folio" n="16r-17v">
<ab>

  </ab>
  </div>
  </div>
  <div type="edition" xml:lang="geez" >
<div type="textpart" subtype="folio" n="18v">
<ab>

  </ab>
  </div>
  </div>

  <div type="edition" xml:lang="geez">
<div type="textpart" subtype="folio" n="8-9r">
<ab>
<pb n="8r"/><cb n="b"/>
ወእንዘ፡ሀለዉ፡ከል፡ኤሆሙ፡ኅቡረ፡<persName ref="PRS6152Lalibala">ላሊበላ፡<roleName type="title">ንጉሥ፡</roleName></persName>ወ<persName ref="PRS6859MasqalK"><roleName type="function">ብእሲቱ፡</roleName>መስቀል፡ክብራ፡<roleName type="title">በአልተ፡ቢሐት፡</roleName></persName>ከመ፡ይኩኖሙ፡መድኃኒተ፡ነፍሶሙ፡በመንግሥተ፡ሰማያት፡ወለብእሲትየኒ፡ከመ፡ይደምራ፡ምስለ፡ቅድ
<pb n="8v"/><cb n="a"/>ሳት፡ምስለ፡ሳራ፡ወ<sic>ሰራሜ፡</sic>ምስለ፡ሐና፡ወሶፍያ፡ወኢይዝከር፡ላቲ፡ኀጢአታ፡ወይደምስስ፡መጸሐፈ፡ጌጋያ፡አሜን።ወአሜን።ለይኩን፡ለይኩን።ወእንዘ፡ሀለዉ፡ዓበይተ፡በኵናት፡
<persName ref="PRS12848Abt"><roleName type="title">ቃለጳስ፡</roleName>አብት፡</persName>
<persName ref="PRS11336Giyorgis"><roleName type="title">ጳጳስ፡</roleName>አባ፡ጊዮርጊስ፡</persName>
<persName ref="PRS5107Harayo"><roleName type="title">ወኤጲስ፡ቆጶስ፡</roleName>ኀረዮ፡</persName>
<persName ref="PRS10332Yerdea"><roleName type="title">ዓቃቤ፡ሰዐት፡መጣዕ፡</roleName>ይርድአነ፡ክርስቶስ፡</persName>
<persName ref="PRS12836Sawen"><roleName type="title">ሊቀ፡ዲያቆናት፡</roleName>ሰውን፡</persName>
<persName ref="PRS12837AbYekun"><roleName type="title">ቀይሰ፡ገበዝ፡ጽዮን፡</roleName>አብ፡ይኩን፡</persName>
<persName ref="PRS12838Yetbarak"><roleName type="title">መልሐዘ፡</roleName>ይትባረክ፡</persName>
<persName ref="PRS12839ZaAdonay"><roleName type="title">ቀስ፡ሐጺን፡</roleName>ዘአዶናየ፡</persName>
<persName ref="PRS12840KrestosBen"><roleName type="title">ጸዋር፡ናርጌ፡መኣሰሬ፡</roleName>ክርስቶስ፡ብነ፡</persName>
<persName ref="PRS12841Sebhat"><roleName type="title">ጸሐፍ፡ላም፡</roleName>ስብሐት፡</persName>
<persName ref="PRS12842Yeqbeena"><roleName type="title">ሐስጓ፡0</roleName>
<cb n="a"/>ይዕቀበነ፡</persName>
<persName ref="PRS12844Asgada"><roleName type="title">ማእከለ፡ባሕር፡</roleName>ኣስገደ፡</persName>
<persName ref="PRS12843BaraSeyon"><roleName type="title">ዕቃ፡ጸንጸን፡</roleName>ባራ፡ጽዮን፡</persName>
<persName ref="PRS12845Yemheranna"><roleName type="title">ዐቃብ፡ደጌ፡ማሰረይ፡</roleName>ይምሐረነ፡</persName>
<persName ref="PRS12846Zarawedem"><roleName type="title">ሊቀ፡አቀይታት፡</roleName>ዘረውድም፡</persName>
እንዘ፡
<persName ref="PRS12847ZaAmalay"><roleName type="title">ሊቀ፡ኬኖት፡</roleName>ዘአመላይ፡</persName>
ወእንዘ፡
<persName ref="PRS12848Yamo"><roleName type="title">ሊቀ፡ኅዳር፡</roleName>ያሞ፡</persName>
<persName ref="PRS12849WaldaBegwenay"><roleName type="title">ሊቀ፡መሰንቆ፡</roleName>ወልደ፡ብጕናይ፡</persName>
ወከመዝ፡ኣጐላትኩ፡ዘኣልቦ፡ግብረ፡ወገብጋበ፡መፍቀሬ፡እግዚአብሔር፡ዘወሀቦ፡<persName ref="PRS6152Lalibala">ላሊበላ፡</persName>ዘንተ፡<sic>ጕልት፡</sic>ዘገፍዐ፡ውጉዘ፡ለይኩን፡አሜን፡ዘንተ፡ዘአጽሐፈ፡
<persName ref="PRS10332Yerdea"><roleName type="title">ዐቃቤ፡ሰዐተ፡መጣዕ፡</roleName>ስመ፡ልደቱ፡ይርድአነ፡ክርስቶስ፡ከመ፡ምንኵስና
<pb n="9r"/><cb n="a"/>ሁ፡ጸጋ፡መጣዕ፡</persName>
ለዘአጽሐፈ፡ስረዩ፡ወባርኩነ፡ኣሜን።
</ab>
</div>
</div>
<div type="edition" xml:lang="en">
<div type="textpart" subtype="folio" n="8-9r">
<ab>
<pb n="8r"/><cb n="8v"/>
And while two were united, <persName ref="PRS6152Lalibala"><roleName type="title">King</roleName>Lālibālā</persName>and<persName ref="PRS6859MasqalK"><roleName type="function">his wife</roleName>Masqal Kǝbra<roleName type="title">baʾalt of Biḥat,
</roleName></persName> so that it become salvation of their souls in the Heavenly Kingdom, and for my wife may it associate her with saint
<pb n="8v"/><cb n="a"/>
women, with Sārā and Salome, with Ḥānnā and Sofiā and may her sin not to be remembered and may the book of her transgressions be obliterated, Amen and Amen.Let it be, let it be.
And while the greats were in strike,
<persName ref="PRS12848Abt"><roleName type="title">qālaṗās</roleName>Abt,</persName>
<persName ref="PRS11336Giyorgis"><roleName type="title">pāpās</roleName><roleName type="title">ʾabuna</roleName>Giyorgis</persName>
and<persName ref="PRS5107Harayo"><roleName type="title">ʾeṗisqoṗos </roleName>Ḫarayo,</persName>
<persName ref="PRS10332Yerdea"><roleName type="title">ʿāqābe saʿāt Maṭāʿ</roleName>Yǝrdǝʾanna Krǝstos,</persName>
<persName ref="PRS12836Sawen"><roleName type="title">liqa diyāqonāt</roleName>Sawǝn,</persName>
<persName ref="PRS12837AbYekun"><roleName type="title">qaysa gabaz Ṣǝyon</roleName>ʾAb Yǝkun,</persName>
<persName ref="PRS12838Yetbarak"><roleName type="title">malḥaza</roleName>Yǝtbārak,</persName>
<persName ref="PRS12839ZaAdonay"><roleName type="title">qas ḥaṣin</roleName>Za-’Adonāya,</persName>
<persName ref="PRS12840KrestosBena"><roleName type="title">ṣawar nārge ma’āsare</roleName>Krǝstos Bǝna,</persName>
<persName ref="PRS12841Sebhat"><roleName type="title">ṣaḥaf lām</roleName>Sǝbḥat,</persName>
<persName ref="PRS12842Yeqbeena"><roleName type="title">ḥasgwā</roleName>
<cb n="b"/>Yǝ‘ǝqabanna,</persName>
<persName ref="PRS12844Asgada"><roleName type="title">mā’ǝkala bāḥr</roleName>ʾAsgada,</persName>
<persName ref="PRS12843BaraSeyon"><roleName type="title">‘ǝqā ṣanṣan</roleName>Bārā Ṣeyon,</persName>
<persName ref="PRS12845Yemheranna"><roleName type="title">‘aqāb dage māsaray</roleName>Yǝmḥaranna,</persName>
<persName ref="PRS12846Zarawedem"><roleName type="title">liqa ’aqqaytāt</roleName>Zara Wǝdǝm,</persName>
while
<persName ref="PRS12847ZaAmalay"><roleName type="title">liqa kenot</roleName>Za-ʾAmalāy</persName>
and while
<persName ref="PRS12848Yamo"><roleName type="title">liqa ḫǝdār</roleName>Yāmo,</persName>
<persName ref="PRS12849WaldaBegwenay"><roleName type="title">liqa masanqo</roleName>Walda Bǝgwǝnāy.</persName>
Thus at that time I promoted this gwǝlt given by <persName ref="PRS6152Lalibala">Lālibālā</persName>, lover of God, without taxation or forced labour; who will restrain this gwǝlt, shall that one be excommunicated, Amen.
This was written upon the request of <persName ref="PRS10332Yerdea"><roleName type="title">ʿāqābe saʿāt Maṭāʿ,</roleName> [named] at birth Yǝrdǝʾanna Krǝstos and  at entering monkhood
 <pb n="9r"/><cb n="a"/>as
 Ṣaggā Maṭāʿ.</persName> Relent that one who requested to write [this] and bless us, Amen.
</ab>
</div>
</div>
</body>
 </text>
</TEI>
